<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha-ha-geo-trouble">
<!--taroth 2013-04-24: fix for bnc#753625-->
 <title>Troubleshooting</title>
 <para>
  Booth
<!--logs to <filename>/var/log/messages</filename> and -->
  uses the same logging mechanism as the CRM. Thus, changing the log level will
  also take effect on booth logging. The booth log messages also contain
  information about any tickets.
 </para>
 <para>
  Both the booth log messages and the booth configuration file are included in
  the <command>crm report</command>.
 </para>
 <para>
  In case of unexpected booth behavior or any problems, check the logging data
  with <command>sudo journalctl -n</command> or create a detailed cluster
  report with <command>crm report</command>.
 </para>
 <para>
  In case you can access the cluster nodes on all sites (plus the arbitrators)
  from one single host via SSH, it is possible to collect log files from all of
  them within the same <literal>crm report</literal>. When calling <command>crm
  report</command> with the <option>-n</option> option, it gets the log files
  from all hosts that you specify with <option>-n</option>. (Without
  <option>-n</option>, it would try to obtain the list of nodes from the
  respective cluster). For example, to create a single <literal>crm
  report</literal> that includes the log files from two two-node clusters
  (<literal>192.168.201.111</literal>|<literal>192.168.201.112</literal> and
  <literal>192.168.202.111</literal>|<literal>192.168.202.112</literal>) plus
  an arbitrator (<literal>147.2.207.14</literal>), use the following command:
 </para>
<screen>&prompt.root; crm report -n "147.2.207.14 192.168.201.111 192.168.201.112 \
 192.168.202.111 192.168.202.112"  -f 10:00 -t 11:00 db-incident</screen>
 <para>
  If the issue is about booth only and you know on which cluster nodes (within
  a site) booth is running, then specify only those two nodes plus the
  arbitrator.
 </para>
 <para>
  If there is no way to access all sites from one host, run <command>crm
  report</command> individually on the arbitrator, and on the cluster nodes of
  the individual sites, specifying the same period of time. To collect the log
  files on an arbitrator, you must use the <option>-S</option> option for
  single node operation:
 </para>
<screen>&cluster1; # crm report -f 10:00 -t 11:00 db-incident-&cluster1;
&cluster2; # crm report -f 10:00 -t 11:00 db-incident-&cluster2;
arbitrator # crm report -S -f 10:00 -t 11:00 db-incident-arbitrator</screen>
 <para>
  However, it is preferable to produce one single <literal>crm report</literal>
  for all machines that you need log files from.
 </para>
</chapter>
