<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha-ha-geo-ip-relocation">
<!--taroth 2014-1120: https://fate.suse.com/316112-->
 <title>Setting up IP relocation via DNS update</title>

 <para>
  In case one site of your &geo; cluster is down and a ticket failover appears,
  you usually need to adjust the network routing accordingly (or you need to
  have configured a network failover for each ticket). Depending on the kind of
  service that is bound to a ticket, there is an alternative solution to
  reconfiguring the routing: You can use dynamic DNS update and instead change
  the IP address for a service.
 </para>
 <para>
  The following prerequisites must be fulfilled for this scenario:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The service that needs to fail over is bound to a host name.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Your DNS server must be configured for dynamic DNS updates. For information
    on how to do so with BIND/named, see the <literal>named</literal>
    documentation, or refer to
    <link xlink:href="http://www.semicomplete.com/articles/dynamic-dns-with-dhcp/"/>.
    <remark>taroth 2014-11-21: lmb, would you consider the aforementioned link appropriate (WRT to
     our customers and the kind of setup that is needed here)?</remark>
    More information on how to set up DNS, including dynamic update of zone
    data, can be found in the <link
     xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles-15/html/SLES-all/cha-dns.html">
     <citetitle>&admin;</citetitle> for &sls; &productnumber;</link>.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The following example assumes that the DNS updates are protected by a
    shared key (TSIG key) for the zone to be updated. The key can be created
    using <command>dnssec-keygen</command>:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>dnssec-keygen</command> -a hmac-md5 -b 128 -n USER geo-update</screen>
   <para>
    For more information, see the <command>dnssec-keygen</command> man page or the
    <link
     xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles-15/html/SLES-all/cha-dns.html#sec-dns-tsig">
     <citetitle>&admin;</citetitle> for &sls; &productnumber;</link>.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  <xref linkend="ex-ha-geo-dyn-dns-rsc-config"/> illustrates how to use the
  <systemitem>ocf:heartbeat:dnsupdate</systemitem> resource agent to manage the
  <command>nsupdate</command>
<!--taroth 2015-01-08: question by the proofreader:
   Should this say 'dnsupdate'? (missing 'd')? - taroth 2016-01-08: for the
   records: nope, correct as is-->
  command.
  <remark>taroth 2014-11-21: lmb, is the following correct? it
   is mentioned in the description of fate#316112, however, your example in c#9 mentions focuses on
   IPv4 only...</remark>
  The resource agent supports both IPv4 and IPv6.
 </para>
 <example xml:id="ex-ha-geo-dyn-dns-rsc-config">
  <title>Resource configuration for dynamic DNS update</title>
<screen>&prompt.crm.conf;<command>primitive</command> dns-update-ip ocf:heartbeat:dnsupdate params \
  hostname="www.domain.com"<co xml:id="co-dyn-dns-hostname"/> ip="192.168.3.4"<co xml:id="co-dyn-dns-ip"/>\
  keyfile="<replaceable>/etc/whereever/Kgeo-update*</replaceable>.key"<co xml:id="co-dyn-dns-key"/>\
  server="192.168.1.1"<co xml:id="co-dyn-dns-srv"/> serverport="53"<co xml:id="co-dyn-dns-srv-port"/></screen>
  <calloutlist>
   <callout arearefs="co-dyn-dns-hostname">
    <para>
     Host name bound to the service that needs to fail over together with the
     ticket. The IP address of this host name needs to be updated via dynamic
     DNS.
    </para>
   </callout>
   <callout arearefs="co-dyn-dns-ip">
    <para>
     IP address of the server hosting the service to be migrated.
     <remark>taroth 2014-11-21:
     lmb, this description taken from fate c#9 is IMHO a bit misleading as it seems to imply that
     this param is about the *current* IP address. However, from the description in
     /usr/lib/ocf/resource.d/heartbeat/dnsupdate, I think this needs to be the IP address that
     will be used for the hostname *after* failover - is that correct?</remark>
     The IP address specified here can be under cluster control, too. This does
     not handle local failover, but it ensures that outside parties will be
     directed to the right site after a ticket failover.
    </para>
   </callout>
   <callout arearefs="co-dyn-dns-key">
    <para>
     Path to the public key file generated with
     <command>dnssec-keygen</command>.
    </para>
   </callout>
   <callout arearefs="co-dyn-dns-srv">
    <para>
     IP address of the DNS server to send the updates to. If no server is
     provided, this defaults to the master server for the correct zone.
    </para>
   </callout>
   <callout arearefs="co-dyn-dns-srv-port">
    <para>
     Port to use for communication with the DNS server. This option will only
     take effect if a DNS server is specified.
    </para>
   </callout>
  </calloutlist>
  <para>
   With the resource configuration above, the resource agent takes care of
   removing the failed &geo; cluster site from the DNS record and changing the
   IP for a service via dynamic DNS update.
  </para>
 </example>
</chapter>
