<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
 %entities;
]>

<chapter id="cha.ha.configuration.gui">
 <title>Configuring and Managing Cluster Resources (GUI)</title>
 <abstract>
  
  <para>To configure and manage cluster resources, either use the graphical
   user interface (the &hbgui;) or the <literal>crm</literal> command line
   utility. For the command line approach, refer to <xref
    linkend="cha.ha.manual_config"/>.</para>

  <para> This chapter introduces the &hbgui; and covers basic tasks needed
   when configuring and managing cluster resources: creating basic and advanced
   types of resources (groups and clones), configuring constraints, specifying
   failover nodes and failback nodes, configuring resource monitoring, starting,
   cleaning up or removing resources, and migrating resources manually. </para>

  <para>Support for the GUI is provided by two packages: The <systemitem
    class="resource">pacemaker-mgmt</systemitem> package contains the back-end
   for the GUI (the <systemitem class="daemon">mgmtd</systemitem> daemon). It
   must be installed on all cluster nodes you want to connect to with the GUI.
   Install the <systemitem class="resource">pacemaker-mgmt-client</systemitem>
   on any machine where you want to run the GUI. </para>
 </abstract>
 <sect1 id="sec.ha.configuration.gui.intro">
  <title>&hbgui;&mdash;Overview</title>
  <para> To start the &hbgui;, enter <command>crm_gui</command> at the
   command line. To access the configuration and administration options, you
   need to log in to a cluster.</para> 
  <sect2 id="sec.ha.configuration.gui.intro.connect">
   <title>Connecting to a Cluster</title>
   <note>
    <title>Password for the <systemitem>hacluster</systemitem> User</title>
    <para> The installation creates a linux user named
      <systemitem>hacluster</systemitem>. Prior to using the &hbgui;, you
     must set the password for the <systemitem>hacluster</systemitem> user. To
     do this, become &rootuser;, enter <command>passwd hacluster</command>
     at the command line and enter a password for the
      <systemitem>hacluster</systemitem> user. </para>
    <para> Do this on every node you will connect to with the &hbgui;.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>To connect to the cluster, select <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Connection</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Login</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>. By default, the <guimenu>Server</guimenu> field shows the
    localhost's IP address and <systemitem>hacluster</systemitem> as
     <guimenu>User Name</guimenu>. Enter the user's password to continue.
   </para>

   <figure pgwide="0">
    <title>Connecting to the Cluster</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="crmgui-login.png" width="45%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="crmgui-login.png" width="45%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <para> If you are running the &hbgui; remotely, enter the IP address of a
    cluster node as <guimenu>Server</guimenu>. As <guimenu>User Name</guimenu>,
    you can also use any other user belonging to the
     <systemitem>haclient</systemitem> group to connect to the cluster. </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.ha.configuration.gui.intro.main">
   <title>Main Window</title>

   <para> After being connected, the main window opens: </para>
   <figure pgwide="0">
    <title>&hbgui; - Main Window</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="crmgui-main.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="crmgui-main.png" width="75%" format="png"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>


   <para>To view or modify cluster components like the CRM, resources, nodes or
    constraints, select the respective subentry of the
     <guimenu>Configuration</guimenu> category in the left pane and use the
    options that become available in the right pane. Additionally, the
    &hbgui; lets you easily view, edit, import and export XML fragments of
    the CIB for the following subitems: <guimenu>Resource Defaults</guimenu>,
     <guimenu>Operation Defaults</guimenu>, <guimenu>Nodes</guimenu>,
     <guimenu>Resources</guimenu>, and <guimenu>Constraints</guimenu>. Select
    any of the <guimenu>Configuration</guimenu> subitems and select <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Show</guimenu>
     <guimenu>XML Mode</guimenu>
    </menuchoice> in the upper right corner of the window.</para>

   <para>If you have already configured your resources, click the
     <guimenu>Management</guimenu> category in the left pane to show the status
    of your cluster and its resources. This view also allows you to set nodes to
     <literal>standby</literal> and to modify the management status of nodes (if
    they are currently managed by the cluster or not). To access the main
    functions for resources (starting, stopping, cleaning up or migrating
    resources), select the resource in the right pane and use the icons in the
    toolbar. Alternatively, right-click the resource and select the respective
    menu item from the context menu.</para>
   <para>The &hbgui; also allows you to switch between different view modes,
    influencing the behavior of the software and hiding or showing certain
    aspects:</para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Simple Mode</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>Lets you add resources in a wizard-like mode. When creating and
       modifying resources, shows the frequently-used tabs for sub-objects,
       allowing you to directly add objects of that type via the tab. </para>
      <para>Allows you to view and change all available global cluster options
       by selecting the <guimenu>CRM Config</guimenu> entry in the left pane.
       The right pane then shows the values that are currently set. If no
       specific value is set for an option, it shows the default values
       instead.</para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Expert Mode</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>Lets you add resources in either a wizard-like mode or via dialog
       windows. When creating and modifying resources, only shows the
       corresponding tab if a particular type of sub-object already exists in
       CIB. When adding a new sub-object, you will prompted to select the object
       type, thus allowing you to add all supported types of sub-objects. </para>
      <para>When selecting the <guimenu>CRM Config</guimenu> entry in the left
       pane, only shows the values of global cluster options that have been
       actually set. Hides all cluster options that will automatically use the
       defaults (because no values have been set). In this mode, the global
       cluster options can only be modified by using the individual
       configuration dialogs.</para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Hack Mode</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>Has the same functions as the expert mode. Allows you to add
       additional attribute sets that include specific rules to make your
       configuration more dynamic. For example, you can make a resource have
       different instance attributes depending on the node it is hosted on.
       Furthermore, you can add a time-based rule for a meta attribute set to
       determine when the attributes take effect.</para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>The window's status bar also shows the currently active mode.</para>

   <para>The following sections guide you through the main tasks you need to
    execute when configuring cluster options and resources and show you how to
    administer the resources with the &hbgui;. Where not stated otherwise,
    the step-by-step instructions reflect the procedure as executed in the
    simple mode.</para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1 id="sec.ha.config.gui.global">
  <title>Configuring Global Cluster Options</title>
  <para> Global cluster options control how the cluster behaves when confronted
   with certain situations. They are grouped into sets and can be viewed and
   modified with the cluster management tools like &hbgui; and
   <command>crm</command> shell. The predefined values can be kept in most cases.
   However, to make key functions of your cluster work correctly, you need to
   adjust the following parameters after basic cluster setup:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.basics.global.quorum"
      xrefstyle="select:title"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.basics.global.stonith"
      xrefstyle="select:title"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <procedure id="pro.ha.config.gui.global">
   <title>Modifying Global Cluster Options</title>
   <step>
    <para>Start the &hbgui; and log in to the cluster as described in <xref
      linkend="sec.ha.configuration.gui.intro.connect"/>.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Select <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>View</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Simple Mode</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>In the left pane, select <guimenu>CRM Config</guimenu> to view the
     global cluster options and their current values. </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Depending on your cluster requirements, set <guimenu>No Quorum
      Policy</guimenu> to the appropriate value.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>If you need to disable fencing for any reasons, deselect
      <literal>Stonith Enabled</literal>. </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Confirm your changes with <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>.</para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>You can at any time switch back to the default values for all options by
   selecting <guimenu>CRM Config</guimenu> in the left pane and clicking
    <guimenu>Default</guimenu>.</para>
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1 id="sec.ha.config.gui.resources">
  <title>Configuring Cluster Resources</title>
  <para>As a cluster administrator, you need to create cluster resources for
   every resource or application you run on servers in your cluster. Cluster
   resources can include Web sites, e-mail servers, databases, file systems,
   virtual machines, and any other server-based applications or services you
   want to make available to users at all times. </para>
  <para>For an overview of resource types you can create, refer to 
   <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.basics.resources.types"/>.</para>

  <sect2 id="sec.ha.configuration.create">
   <title>Creating Simple Cluster Resources</title>
   <para>To create the most basic type of a resource, proceed as follows:</para>
   <procedure id="pro.ha.config.gui.primitives">
    <title>Adding Primitive Resources</title>
    <step id="st.ha.configuration.create.start">
     <para>Start the &hbgui; and log in to the cluster as described in
       <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.gui.intro.connect"/>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In the left pane, select <guimenu>Resources</guimenu> and click <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Add</guimenu>
       <guimenu>Primitive</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In the next dialog, set the following parameters for the resource: </para>
     <substeps>
      <step>
       <para> Enter a unique <guimenu>ID</guimenu> for the resource. </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para> From the <guimenu>Class</guimenu> list, select the resource agent
        class you want to use for that resource: <guimenu>heartbeat</guimenu>,
         <guimenu>lsb</guimenu>, <guimenu>ocf</guimenu> or
         <guimenu>stonith</guimenu>. For more information, see <xref
         linkend="sec.ha.resources.raclasses"/>. </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para> If you selected <guimenu>ocf</guimenu> as class, specify also the
         <guimenu>Provider</guimenu> of your OCF resource agent. The OCF
        specification allows multiple vendors to supply the same resource agent.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para> From the <guimenu>Type</guimenu> list, select the resource agent
        you want to use (for example, <guimenu>IPaddr</guimenu> or
         <guimenu>Filesystem</guimenu>). A short description for this resource
        agent is displayed below. </para>
       <para> The selection you get in the <guimenu>Type</guimenu> list depends
        on the <guimenu>Class</guimenu> (and for OCF resources also on the
         <guimenu>Provider</guimenu>) you have chosen. </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para> Below <guimenu>Options</guimenu>, set the <guimenu>Initial state
         of resource</guimenu>. </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para> Activate <guimenu>Add monitor operation</guimenu> if you want the
        cluster to monitor if the resource is still healthy. </para>
       <informalfigure>
        <mediaobject>
         <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="crmgui-primitive-basic.png" width="70%"
           format="PNG"/>
         </imageobject>
         <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="crmgui-primitive-basic.png" width="70%"
           format="png"/>
         </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
       </informalfigure>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Click <guimenu>Forward</guimenu>. The next window shows a summary of
      the parameters that you have already defined for that resource. All
      required <guimenu>Instance Attributes</guimenu> for that resource are
      listed. You need to edit them in order to set them to appropriate values.
      You may also need to add more attributes, depending on your deployment and
      settings. For details how to do so, refer to <xref
       linkend="pro.ha.config.gui.parameters"/>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> If all parameters are set according to your wishes, click
       <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> to finish the configuration of that resource.
      The configuration dialog is closed and the main window shows the newly
      added resource. </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>

   <para>During or after creation of a resource, you can add or modify the
    following parameters for resources: <literal>instance attributes</literal>
    (determining which instance of a service the resource controls),
     <literal>meta attributes</literal> (telling the CRM how to treat a specific
    resource), and <literal>operations</literal> (needed for resource
    monitoring). For more information on the parameters, refer to <xref
     linkend="sec.ha.configuration.basics.resources.parameters"/>.</para>

   <procedure id="pro.ha.config.gui.parameters">
    <title>Adding or Modifying Meta and Instance Attributes</title>
    <step>
     <para>In the &hbgui; main window, click <guimenu>Resources</guimenu>
      in the left pane to see the resources already configured for the cluster.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In the right pane, select the resource to modify and click
       <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> (or double-click the resource). The next window
      shows the basic resource parameters and the <guimenu>Meta
       Attributes</guimenu>, <guimenu>Instance Attributes</guimenu> or
       <guimenu>Operations</guimenu> already defined for that resource. </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="crmgui-primitive-attributes.png" width="40%"
         format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="crmgui-primitive-attributes.png" width="40%"
         format="png"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>To add a new meta attribute or instance attribute, select the
      respective tab and click <guimenu>Add</guimenu>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Select the <guimenu>Name</guimenu> of the attribute you want to add.
      A short <guimenu>Description</guimenu> is displayed. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> If needed, specify an attribute <guimenu>Value</guimenu>. Otherwise
      the default value of that attribute will be used. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to confirm your changes. The newly added
      or modified attribute appears on the tab. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> If all parameters are set according to your wishes, click
       <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to finish the configuration of that resource. The
      configuration dialog is closed and the main window shows the modified
      resource. </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>

   <tip>
    <title>XML Source Code for Resources</title>
    <para>The &hbgui; allows you to view the XML fragments that are
     generated from the parameters that you have defined. For individual
     resources, select <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Show</guimenu>
      <guimenu>XML Mode</guimenu>
     </menuchoice> in the top right corner of the resource configuration
     dialog.</para>
    <para>To access the XML representation of all resources that you have
     configured, click <guimenu>Resources</guimenu> in the left pane and then
     select <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Show</guimenu>
      <guimenu>XML Mode</guimenu>
     </menuchoice> in the upper right corner of the main window. </para>
    <para> The editor displaying the XML code allows you to
      <guimenu>Import</guimenu> or <guimenu>Export</guimenu> the XML elements or
     to manually edit the XML code.</para>
   </tip>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.ha.configuration.stonith">
   <title>Creating &stonith; Resources</title>

   <para> To configure fencing, you need to configure one or more &stonith;
    resources. </para>

   <procedure os="pro.ha.config.gui.stonith">
    <title>Adding a &stonith; Resource</title>
    <step>
     <para> Start the &hbgui; and log in to the cluster as described in
       <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.gui.intro.connect"/>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In the left pane, select <guimenu>Resources</guimenu> and click <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Add</guimenu>
       <guimenu>Primitive</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In the next dialog, set the following parameters for the resource: </para>
     <substeps>
      <step>
       <para> Enter a unique <guimenu>ID</guimenu> for the resource. </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para> From the <guimenu>Class</guimenu> list, select the resource agent
        class <guimenu>stonith</guimenu>. </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para> From the <guimenu>Type</guimenu> list, select the &stonith;
        plug-in for controlling your &stonith; device. A short description
        for this plug-in is displayed below. </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para> Below <guimenu>Options</guimenu>, set the <guimenu>Initial state
         of resource</guimenu>. </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para> Activate <guimenu>Add monitor operation</guimenu> if you want the
        cluster to monitor the fencing device. For more information, refer to
         <xref linkend="sec.ha.fencing.monitor"/>. </para>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Click <guimenu>Forward</guimenu>. The next window shows a summary of
      the parameters that you have already defined for that resource. All
      required <guimenu>Instance Attributes</guimenu> for the selected
      &stonith; plug-in are listed. You need to edit them in order to set
      them to appropriate values. You may also need to add more attributes or
      monitor operations, depending on your deployment and settings. For details
      how to do so, refer to <xref linkend="pro.ha.config.gui.parameters"/> and
       <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.monitor"/>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> If all parameters are set according to your wishes, click
       <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> to finish the configuration of that resource.
      The configuration dialog is closed and the main window shows the newly
      added resource. </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>

   <para> To complete your fencing configuration add constraints, or use clones
    or both. For more details, refer to <xref linkend="cha.ha.fencing"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.ha.configuration.constraints">
   <title>Configuring Resource Constraints</title>

   <para>
    Having all the resources configured is only part of the job. Even if the
    cluster knows all needed resources, it might still not be able to handle
    them correctly. Resource constraints let you specify which cluster nodes
    resources can run on, what order resources will load, and what other
    resources a specific resource is dependent on.
   </para>
   <para>For an overview which types of constraints are available, refer to
     <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.basics.constraints.types"/>. When
    defining constraints, you also need to specify scores. For more information
    about scores and their implications in the cluster, see <xref
    linkend="sec.ha.configuration.basics.constraints.scores"/>.</para>  
   <para>Learn how to create the different types of the constraints in the
    following procedures. </para>
   <procedure id="pro.ha.config.gui.constraints.location">
    <title>Adding or Modifying Locational Constraints</title>
    <step id="step.ha.configuration.constraints.start">
     <para> Start the &hbgui; and log in to the cluster as described in
       <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.gui.intro.connect"/>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In the &hbgui; main window, click <guimenu>Constraints</guimenu>
      in the left pane to see the constraints already configured for the
      cluster. </para>
    </step>
    <step id="step.ha.configuration.constraints.stop">
     <para> In the left pane, select <guimenu>Constraints</guimenu> and click
       <guimenu>Add</guimenu>. </para>
     <!--<para>Or select an existing constraint and click
     <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>.</para>-->
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Select <guimenu>Resource Location</guimenu> and click
       <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Enter a unique <guimenu>ID</guimenu> for the constraint. When
      modifying existing constraints, the ID is already defined and is displayed
      in the configuration dialog. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Select the <guimenu>Resource</guimenu> for which to define the
      constraint. The list shows the IDs of all resources that have been
      configured for the cluster. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Set the <guimenu>Score</guimenu> for the constraint. Positive values
      indicate the resource can run on the <guimenu>Node</guimenu> you specify
      below. Negative values indicate the resource can not run on this node.
      Values of <literal>+/- INFINITY</literal> change <quote>can</quote> to
       <literal>must</literal>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Select the <guimenu>Node</guimenu> for the constraint. </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="crmgui-constraint-location.png" width="45%"
         format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="crmgui-constraint-location.png" width="45%"
         format="png"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      <remark>taroth 090325: todo - probably this is not the right place to
       mention this... check for better place</remark> If you leave the
       <guimenu>Node</guimenu> and the <guimenu>Score</guimenu> field empty, you
      can also add rules by clicking <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Add</guimenu>
       <guimenu>Rule</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>. To add a lifetime, just click <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Add</guimenu>
       <guimenu>Lifetime</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> If all parameters are set according to your wishes, click
       <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to finish the configuration of the constraint. The
      configuration dialog is closed and the main window shows the newly added
      or modified constraint. </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>

   <procedure id="pro.ha.config.gui.constraints.collocation">
    <title>Adding or Modifying Collocational Constraints</title>
    <step>
     <para> Start the &hbgui; and log in to the cluster as described in
       <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.gui.intro.connect"/>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In the &hbgui; main window, click <guimenu>Constraints</guimenu>
      in the left pane to see the constraints already configured for the
      cluster. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In the left pane, select <guimenu>Constraints</guimenu> and click
       <guimenu>Add</guimenu>. </para>
     <!--<para>Or select an existing constraint and click
     <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>.</para>-->
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Select <guimenu>Resource Collocation</guimenu> and click
       <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Enter a unique <guimenu>ID</guimenu> for the constraint. When
      modifying existing constraints, the ID is already defined and is displayed
      in the configuration dialog. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Select the <guimenu>Resource</guimenu> which is the collocation
      source. The list shows the IDs of all resources that have been configured
      for the cluster. </para>
     <para> If the constraint cannot be satisﬁed, the cluster may decide not to
      allow the resource to run at all. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      <remark>taroth 090331: todo - probably this is not the right place to
       mention this... check for better place</remark> If you leave both the
       <guimenu>Resource</guimenu> and the <guimenu>With Resource</guimenu>
      field empty, you can also add a resource set by clicking <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Add</guimenu>
       <guimenu>Resource Set</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>. To add a lifetime, just click <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Add</guimenu>
       <guimenu>Lifetime</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In <guimenu>With Resource</guimenu>, define the collocation target.
      The cluster will decide where to put this resource ﬁrst and then decide
      where to put the resource in the <guimenu>Resource</guimenu> ﬁeld. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Define a <guimenu>Score</guimenu> to determine the location
      relationship between both resources. Positive values indicate the
      resources should run on the same node. Negative values indicate the
      resources should not run on the same node. Values of <literal>+/-
       INFINITY</literal> change <literal>should</literal> to
       <literal>must</literal>. The score will be combined with other factors to
      decide where to put the resource. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> If needed, specify further parameters, like <guimenu>Resource
       Role</guimenu>. </para>
     <para> Depending on the parameters and options you choose, a short
       <guimenu>Description</guimenu> explains the effect of the collocational
      constraint you are configuring. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> If all parameters are set according to your wishes, click
       <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to finish the configuration of the constraint. The
      configuration dialog is closed and the main window shows the newly added
      or modified constraint. </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>

   <procedure id="pro.ha.config.gui.constraints.order">
    <title>Adding or Modifying Ordering Constraints</title>
    <step>
     <para> Start the &hbgui; and log in to the cluster as described in
       <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.gui.intro.connect"/>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In the &hbgui; main window, click <guimenu>Constraints</guimenu>
      in the left pane to see the constraints already configured for the
      cluster. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In the left pane, select <guimenu>Constraints</guimenu> and click
       <guimenu>Add</guimenu>. </para>
     <!--<para>Or select an existing constraint and click
     <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>.</para>-->
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Select <guimenu>Resource Order</guimenu> and click
       <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Enter a unique <guimenu>ID</guimenu> for the constraint. When
      modifying existing constraints, the ID is already defined and is displayed
      in the configuration dialog. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> With <guimenu>First</guimenu>, define the resource that must be
      started before the resource specified with <guimenu>Then</guimenu> is
      allowed to. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> With <guimenu>Then</guimenu> define the resource that will start
      after the <guimenu>First</guimenu> resource. </para>
     <para>Depending on the parameters and options you choose, a short
       <guimenu>Description</guimenu> explains the effect of the ordering
      constraint you are configuring. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> If needed, define further parameters, for example:</para>
     <substeps>
      <step>
       <para>Specify a <guimenu>Score</guimenu>. If greater than zero, the
        constraint is mandatory, otherwise it is only a suggestion. The default
        value is <literal>INFINITY</literal>.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>Specify a value for <guimenu>Symmetrical</guimenu>. If
         <literal>true</literal>, the resources are stopped in the reverse
        order. The default value is <literal>true</literal>.</para>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> If all parameters are set according to your wishes, click
       <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to finish the configuration of the constraint. The
      configuration dialog is closed and the main window shows the newly added
      or modified constraint. </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>

   <para> You can access and modify all constraints that you have configured in
    the <guimenu>Constraints</guimenu> view of the &hbgui;. </para>

   <figure>
    <title>&hbgui; - Constraints</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="crmgui-main-constraints.png" width="68%" format="PNG"
      />
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="crmgui-main-constraints.png" width="68%" format="png"
      />
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.ha.configuration.failover">
   <title>Specifying Resource Failover Nodes</title>

   <para> A resource will be automatically restarted if it fails. If that cannot
    be achieved on the current node, or it fails N times on the current node, it
    will try to fail over to another node. You can define a number of failures
    for resources (a <literal>migration-threshold</literal>), after which they
    will migrate to a new node. If you have more than two nodes in your cluster,
    the node a particular resource fails over to is chosen by the &ha;
    software. </para>

   <para>However, you can specify the node a resource will fail over to by
    proceeding as follows:</para>

   <procedure id="pro.ha.config.gui.failover">
    <step>
     <para> Configure a location constraint for that resource as described in
       <xref linkend="pro.ha.config.gui.constraints.location"/>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Add the <literal>migration-threshold</literal> meta attribute to
      that resource as described in <xref linkend="pro.ha.config.gui.parameters"
      /> and enter a <guimenu>Value</guimenu> for the migration-threshold. The
      value should be positive and less that INFINITY. </para>
     <!-- <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="crmgui-primitive-migr-threshold.png" width="45%"
        format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="crmgui-primitive-migr-threshold.png" width="45%"
        format="png"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>-->
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>If you want to automatically expire the failcount for a resource,
      add the <literal>failure-timeout</literal> meta attribute to that resource
      as described in <xref linkend="pro.ha.config.gui.parameters"/> and enter a
       <guimenu>Value</guimenu> for the failure-timeout. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>If you want to specify additional failover nodes with preferences
      for a resource, create additional location constraints. </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   
   <para>For an example of the process flow in the cluster regarding
    migration thresholds and failcounts, see <xref
     linkend="ex.ha.config.basics.failover"/>.</para>

   <para>Instead of letting the failcount for a resource expire automatically,
    you can also clean up failcounts for a resource manually at any time. Refer
    to <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.cleanup"/> for the details.</para>
   
   
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.ha.configuration.failback">
   <title>Specifying Resource Failback Nodes (Resource Stickiness)</title>

   <para> A resource might fail back to its original node when that node is back
    online and in the cluster. If you want to prevent a resource from failing
    back to the node it was running on prior to failover, or if you want to
    specify a different node for the resource to fail back to, you must change
    its resource stickiness value. You can either specify resource stickiness
    when you are creating a resource, or afterwards. </para>
   
   <para>For the implications of different resource stickiness values, refer  to
    <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.basics.failback"/>.
   </para>
   <procedure id="pro.ha.config.gui.stickiness">
    <title>Specifying Resource Stickiness</title>
    <step>
     <para> Add the <literal>resource-stickiness</literal> meta attribute to the
      resource as described in <xref linkend="pro.ha.config.gui.parameters"/>. </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="crmgui-primitive-stickiness.png" width="55%"
         format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="crmgui-primitive-stickiness.png" width="55%"
         format="png"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> As <guimenu>Value</guimenu> for the resource-stickiness, specify a
      value between <literal>-INFINITY</literal> and
      <literal>INFINITY</literal>. </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.ha.configuration.utilization">
   <title>Configuring Placement of Resources Based on Load Impact</title>
   <para>Not all resources are equal. Some, such as &xen; guests, require
    that the node hosting them meets their capacity requirements. If resources
    are placed such that their combined need exceed the provided capacity, the
    resources diminish in performance (or even fail).</para>
   <para>To take this into account, the &hasi; allows you to specify the
    following parameters:</para>
   <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>The capacity a certain node <emphasis>provides</emphasis>.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>The capacity a certain resource <emphasis>requires</emphasis>.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>An overall strategy for placement of resources.</para>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
    <para>For detailed background information about the parameters and a
    configuration example, refer to <xref
    linkend="sec.ha.configuration.basics.utilization"/>.</para>
   <para>To configure the resource's requirements and the capacity a node
    provides, use utilization attributes as described in <xref
     linkend="pro.ha.config.gui.capacity"/>. You can name the utilization
    attributes according to your preferences and define as many name/value pairs
    as your configuration needs. 
   </para>

   <procedure id="pro.ha.config.gui.capacity">
    <title>Adding Or Modifying Utilization Attributes</title>
    <para>In the following example, we assume that you already have a basic
     configuration of cluster nodes and resources and now additionally want to
     configure the capacities a certain node provides and the capacity a certain
     resource requires. The procedure of adding utilization attributes is
     basically the same and only differs in <xref
      linkend="step.ha.config.gui.capacity.node"/> and <xref
      linkend="step.ha.config.gui.capacity.resource"/>. </para>
    <step>
     <para> Start the &hbgui; and log in to the cluster as described in
       <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.gui.intro.connect"/>. </para>
    </step>
    <step id="step.ha.config.gui.capacity.node">
     <para>To specify the capacity a node <emphasis>provides</emphasis>:</para>
     <substeps>
      <step>
       <para>In the left pane, click <guimenu>Node</guimenu>.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>In the right pane, select the node whose capacity you want to
        configure and click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>.</para>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
    <step id="step.ha.config.gui.capacity.resource">
     <para>To specify the capacity a resource
      <emphasis>requires</emphasis>:</para>
     <substeps>
      <step>
       <para>In the left pane, click <guimenu>Resources</guimenu>.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>In the right pane, select the resource whose capacity you want to
        configure and click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>.</para>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Select the <guimenu>Utilization</guimenu> tab and click
       <guimenu>Add</guimenu> to add an utilization attribute. </para>
    </step>
    <step id="step.ha.config.gui.capacity.attr.name">
     <para>Enter a <guimenu>Name</guimenu> for the new attribute. You can name
      the utilization attributes according to your preferences. </para>
    </step>
    <step id="step.ha.config.gui.capacity.attr.value">
     <para>Enter a <guimenu>Value</guimenu> for the attribute and click
       <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. The attribute value must be an integer.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>If you need more utilization attributes, repeat <xref
       linkend="step.ha.config.gui.capacity.attr.name"/> to <xref
       linkend="step.ha.config.gui.capacity.attr.value"/>. </para>
     <para>The <guimenu>Utilization</guimenu> tab shows a summary of the
      utilization attributes that you have already defined for that node or
      resource.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>If all parameters are set according to your wishes, click
       <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to close the configuration dialog.</para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>The following example shows the configuration of a node which would
    provide 8 CPU units and 16 GB of memory to resources running on that
    node:</para>
   <figure>
    <title>Example Configuration for Node Capacity</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="crmgui-node-utilization.png" width="45%" format="PNG"
      />
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="crmgui-node-utilization.png" width="45%" format="PNG"
      />
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>An example configuration for a resource requiring 4096 memory units and
    4 of the CPU units of a node would look as follows: </para>
   <figure>
    <title>Example Configuration for Resource Capacity</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="crmgui-resource-utilization.png" width="45%"
       format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="crmgui-resource-utilization.png" width="45%"
       format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>After you have configured the capacities your nodes provide and the
    capacities your resources require, you need to set the placement strategy in
    the global cluster options, otherwise the capacity configurations have no
    effect. Several strategies are available to schedule the load: for example,
    you can concentrate it on as few nodes as possible, or balance it evenly
    over all available nodes. For more information, refer to <xref
     linkend="sec.ha.configuration.basics.utilization"/>.</para>
   <procedure id="pro.ha.config.gui.placement">
    <title>Setting the Placement Strategy</title>
    <step>
     <para>Start the &hbgui; and log in to the cluster as described in <xref
       linkend="sec.ha.configuration.gui.intro.connect"/>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Select <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>View</guimenu>
       <guimenu>Simple Mode</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>In the left pane, select <guimenu>CRM Config</guimenu> to view the
      global cluster options and their current values. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Depending on your requirements, set <guimenu>Placement
       Strategy</guimenu> to the appropriate value.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>If you need to disable fencing for any reasons, deselect
       <literal>Stonith Enabled</literal>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Confirm your changes with <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>.</para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2 id="sec.ha.configuration.monitor">
   <title>Configuring Resource Monitoring</title>

   <para> Although the &hasi; can detect a node failure, it also has the
    ability to detect when an individual resource on a node has failed. If you
    want to ensure that a resource is running, you must configure resource
    monitoring for it. Resource monitoring consists of specifying a timeout
    and/or start delay value, and an interval. The interval tells the CRM how
    often it should check the resource status. You can also set particular
    parameters, such as <literal>Timeout</literal> for <literal>start</literal>
    or <literal>stop</literal> operations. </para>

   <procedure id="pro.ha.config.gui.operations">
    <title>Adding or Modifying Monitor Operations</title>
    <step>
     <para> Start the &hbgui; and log in to the cluster as described in
       <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.gui.intro.connect"/>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In the &hbgui; main window, click <guimenu>Resources</guimenu>
      in the left pane to see the resources already configured for the cluster.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In the right pane, select the resource to modify and click
       <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>. The next window shows the basic resource
      parameters and the meta attributes, instance attributes and operations
      already defined for that resource. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> To add a new monitor operation, select the respective tab and click
       <guimenu>Add</guimenu>. </para>
     <para> To modify an existing operation, select the respective entry and
      click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>. </para>
    </step>
    <!-- ygao 2010-03-01: currently for "Simple Mode", the ID is automatically generated by GUI,
     so user no longer needs to enter one.-->
     <!--<step>
     <para> Enter a unique <guimenu>ID</guimenu> for the monitor operation. When
      modifying existing monitor operations, the ID is already defined and is
      displayed in the configuration dialog. </para>
    </step>-->
    <step>
     <para>In <guimenu>Name</guimenu>, select the action to perform, for
      example <literal>monitor</literal>, <literal>start</literal>, or
       <guimenu>stop</guimenu>. </para>
     <para>The parameters shown below depend on the selection you make
      here.</para>
    </step>
   <step>
     <para> In the <guimenu>Timeout</guimenu> field, enter a value in seconds.
      After the specified timeout period, the operation will be treated as
       <literal>failed</literal>. The PE will decide what to do or execute what
      you specified in the <guimenu>On Fail</guimenu> field of the monitor
      operation. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>If needed, expand the <guimenu>Optional</guimenu> section and add
      parameters, like <guimenu>On Fail</guimenu> (what do if this action ever
      fails?) or <guimenu>Requires</guimenu> (what conditions need to be
      satisfied before this action occurs?). </para>
     <remark>taroth 2010-03-01: todo - update screenshot (ID field not shown any
      longer)</remark>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="crmgui-primitive-monitor.png" width="35%"
         format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="crmgui-primitive-monitor.png" width="35%"
         format="png"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> If all parameters are set according to your wishes, click
       <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to finish the configuration of that resource. The
      configuration dialog is closed and the main window shows the modified
      resource. </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>For the processes which take place if the resource monitor detects a
    failure, refer to <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.basics.monitoring"/>.
   </para>
   <para>To view resource failures in the &hbgui;, click
     <guimenu>Management</guimenu> in the left pane, then select the resource
    whose details you want to see in the right pane. For a resource that has
    failed, the <guimenu>Fail Count</guimenu> and last failure of the resource
    is shown in the middle of the right pane (below the <guimenu>Migration
     threshold</guimenu> entry).</para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.ha.configuration.group">
   <title>Configuring a Cluster Resource Group</title>

   <para>Some cluster resources are dependent on other components or resources,
    and require that each component or resource starts in a specific order and
    runs together on the same server. To simplify this configuration we support
    the concept of groups.</para>
   <para>For an example of a resource group and more information about groups
    and their properties, refer to <xref
     linkend="sec.ha.configuration.basics.resources.advanced.groups"/>.</para>

   <note>
    <title>Empty Groups</title>
    <para> Groups must contain at least one resource, otherwise the
     configuration is not valid. </para>
   </note>

   <procedure id="pro.ha.config.gui.group">
    <title>Adding a Resource Group</title>
    <step>
     <para> Start the &hbgui; and log in to the cluster as described in
       <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.gui.intro.connect"/>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In the left pane, select <guimenu>Resources</guimenu> and click <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Add</guimenu>
       <guimenu>Group</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Enter a unique <guimenu>ID</guimenu> for the group. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Below <guimenu>Options</guimenu>, set the <guimenu>Initial state of
       resource</guimenu> and click <guimenu>Forward</guimenu>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In the next step, you can add primitives as sub-resources for the
      group. These are created similar as described in <xref
       linkend="pro.ha.config.gui.primitives"/>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> If all parameters are set according to your wishes, click
       <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> to finish the configuration of the primitive.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In the next window, you can continue adding sub-resources for the
      group by choosing <guimenu>Primitive</guimenu> again and clicking
       <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. </para>
     <para> When you do not want to add more primitives to the group, click
       <guimenu>Cancel</guimenu> instead. The next window shows a summary of the
      parameters that you have already defined for that group. The <guimenu>Meta
       Attributes</guimenu> and <guimenu>Primitives</guimenu> of the group are
      listed. The position of the resources in the <guimenu>Primitive</guimenu>
      tab represents the order in which the resources are started in the
      cluster. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> As the order of resources in a group is important, use the
       <guimenu>Up</guimenu> and <guimenu>Down</guimenu> buttons to sort the
       <guimenu>Primitives</guimenu> in the group. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> If all parameters are set according to your wishes, click
       <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to finish the configuration of that group. The
      configuration dialog is closed and the main window shows the newly created
      or modified group. </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>

   <figure>
    <title>&hbgui; - Groups</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="crmgui-main-groups.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="crmgui-main-groups.png" width="65%" format="png"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  
   <para>Let us assume you already have created a resource group as explained in
     <xref linkend="pro.ha.config.gui.group"/>. The following procedure shows
    you how to modify the group to match <xref
     linkend="ex.ha.config.resource.group"/>.</para> 

   <procedure id="pro.ha.config.gui.group.modify">
    <title>Adding Resources to an Existing Group</title>
    <step>
     <para> Start the &hbgui; and log in to the cluster as described in
       <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.gui.intro.connect"/>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In the left pane, switch to the <guimenu>Resources</guimenu> view
      and in the right pane, select the group to modify and click
       <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>. The next window shows the basic group parameters
      and the meta attributes and primitives already defined for that resource.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Click the <guimenu>Primitives</guimenu> tab and click
       <guimenu>Add</guimenu>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In the next dialog, set the following parameters to add an IP
      address as sub-resource of the group: </para>
     <substeps>
      <step id="step.ha.config.gui.group.prim.start">
       <para> Enter a unique <guimenu>ID</guimenu> (for example,
         <literal>my_ipaddress</literal>). </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para> From the <guimenu>Class</guimenu> list, select
         <guimenu>ocf</guimenu> as resource agent class. </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para> As <guimenu>Provider</guimenu> of your OCF resource agent, select
         <guimenu>heartbeat</guimenu>. </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para> From the <guimenu>Type</guimenu> list, select
         <guimenu>IPaddr</guimenu> as resource agent. </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para> Click <guimenu>Forward</guimenu>. </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para> In the <guimenu>Instance Attribute</guimenu> tab, select the
         <guimenu>IP</guimenu> entry and click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> (or
        double-click the <guimenu>IP</guimenu> entry). </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para> As <guimenu>Value</guimenu>, enter the desired IP address, for
        example, <literal>192.168.1.1</literal>. </para>
      </step>
      <step id="step.ha.config.gui.group.prim.stop">
       <para> Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> and <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>. The
        group configuration dialog shows the newly added primitive. </para>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Add the next sub-resources (file system and Web server) by clicking
       <guimenu>Add</guimenu> again. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Set the respective parameters for each of the sub-resources similar
      to steps <xref linkend="step.ha.config.gui.group.prim.start"/> to <xref
       linkend="step.ha.config.gui.group.prim.stop"/>, until you have configured
      all sub-resources for the group. </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="crmgui-resource-group.png" width="50%" format="PNG"
        />
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="crmgui-resource-group.png" width="45%" format="png"
        />
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
     <para> As we configured the sub-resources already in the order in that they
      need to be started in the cluster, the order on the
       <guimenu>Primitives</guimenu> tab is already correct. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In case you need to change the resource order for a group, use the
       <guimenu>Up</guimenu> and <guimenu>Down</guimenu> buttons to sort the
      resources on the <guimenu>Primitive</guimenu> tab. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> To remove a resource from the group, select the resource on the
       <guimenu>Primitives</guimenu> tab and click <guimenu>Remove</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to finish the configuration of that
      group. The configuration dialog is closed and the main window shows the
      modified group. </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.ha.configuration.clone">
   <title>Configuring a Clone Resource</title>

   <para> You may want certain resources to run simultaneously on multiple nodes
    in your cluster. To do this you must configure a resource as a clone.
    Examples of resources that might be configured as clones include
    &stonith; and cluster file systems like OCFS2. You can clone any
    resource provided it is supported by the resource’s Resource Agent. Clone
    resources may even be configured differently depending on which nodes they
    are hosted. </para>

   <para>For an overview which types of resource clones are available, refer to
     <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.basics.resources.advanced.clones"/>.
   </para>

   <procedure id="pro.ha.config.gui.clone">
    <title>Adding or Modifying Clones</title>
    <step>
     <para> Start the &hbgui; and log in to the cluster as described in
       <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.gui.intro.connect"/>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In the left pane, select <guimenu>Resources</guimenu> and click <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Add</guimenu>
       <guimenu>Clone</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Enter a unique <guimenu>ID</guimenu> for the clone. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Below <guimenu>Options</guimenu>, set the <guimenu>Initial state of
       resource</guimenu>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Activate the respective options you want to set for your clone and
      click <guimenu>Forward</guimenu>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In the next step, you can either add a <guimenu>Primitive</guimenu>
      or a <guimenu>Group</guimenu> as sub-resources for the clone. These are
      created similar as described in <xref
       linkend="pro.ha.config.gui.primitives"/> or <xref
       linkend="pro.ha.config.gui.group"/>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> If all parameters in the clone configuration dialog are set
      according to your wishes, click <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> to finish the
      configuration of the clone. </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1 id="sec.ha.config.gui.manage">
  <title>Managing Cluster Resources</title>
  <para>Apart from the possibility to configure your cluster resources, the
   &hbgui; also allows you to manage existing resources. To switch to a
   management view and to access the available options, click
    <guimenu>Management</guimenu> in the left pane.</para>
  
  <figure>
   <title>&hbgui; - Management</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="crmgui-main-manage.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="crmgui-main-manage.png" width="65%" format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  
  <sect2 id="sec.ha.configuration.start">
   <title>Starting Resources</title>
   <para>Before you start a cluster resource, make sure it is set up correctly.
    For example, if you want to use an Apache server as a cluster resource, set
    up the Apache server first and complete the Apache configuration before
    starting the respective resource in your cluster.</para>
   <note>
    <title>Do Not Touch Services Managed by the Cluster</title>
    <para> When managing a resource with the &hasi;, the same resource must
     not be started or stopped otherwise (outside of the cluster, for example
     manually or on boot or reboot). The &hasi; software is responsible for
     all service start or stop actions.</para>
    <para>However, if you want to check if the service is configured properly,
     start it manually, but make sure that it is stopped again before &ha;
     takes over.</para>
    <para>For interventions in resources that are currently managed by the
     cluster, set the resource to <literal>unmanaged mode</literal> first as
     described in <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.mgmt.mode"/>.</para>
   </note>
   <para>During creation of a resource with the &hbgui;, you can set the
    resource's initial state with the <literal>target-role</literal> meta
    attribute. If its value has been set to <literal>stopped</literal>, the
    resource does not start automatically after being created.</para>
   <procedure id="pro.ha.config.gui.start">
    <title>Starting A New Resource </title>
    <step>
     <para>Start the &hbgui; and log in to the cluster as described in <xref
       linkend="sec.ha.configuration.gui.intro.connect"/>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Click <guimenu>Management</guimenu> in the left pane. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>In the right pane, right-click the resource and select
       <guimenu>Start</guimenu> from the context menu (or use the <guimenu>Start
       Resource</guimenu> icon in the toolbar).</para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.ha.configuration.cleanup">
   <title>Cleaning Up Resources</title>
   <para>A resource will be automatically restarted if it fails, but each
    failure raises the resource's failcount. View a resource's failcount with
    the &hbgui; my clicking <guimenu>Management</guimenu> in the left pane,
    then selecting the resource in the right pane. If a resource has failed, its
     <guimenu>Fail Count</guimenu> is shown in the middle of the right pane
    (below the <guimenu>Migration Threshold</guimenu> entry).</para>
   <para>If a <literal>migration-threshold</literal> has been set for that
    resource, the node will no longer be allowed to run the resource as soon as
    the number of failures has reached the migration threshold. </para>
   <para>A resource's failcount can either be reset automatically (by setting a
     <literal>failure-timeout</literal> option for the resource) or you can
    reset it manually as described below.</para>
   <procedure id="pro.ha.config.gui.clean">
    <title>Cleaning Up A Resource</title>
    <step>
     <para>Start the &hbgui; and log in to the cluster as described in <xref
       linkend="sec.ha.configuration.gui.intro.connect"/>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Click <guimenu>Management</guimenu> in the left pane.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>In the right pane, right-click the respective resource and select
       <guimenu>Cleanup Resource</guimenu> from the context menu (or use the
       <guimenu>Cleanup Resource</guimenu> icon in the toolbar). </para>
     <para>This executes the commands
        <command>crm_resource&nbsp;<option>-C</option></command> and
        <command>crm_failcount&nbsp;<option>-D</option></command> for the
      specified resource on the specified node. </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>For more information, see also <xref linkend="man.crmresource"/> and
     <xref linkend="man.crmfailcount"/>. </para>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2 id="sec.ha.configuration.remove">
  <title>Removing Cluster Resources</title>
   <para>If you need to remove a resource from the cluster, follow the procedure
   below to avoid configuration errors:</para>
   <!--https://bugzilla.novell.com/show_bug.cgi?id=520718-->
   <note>
    <title>Removing Referenced Resources</title>
    <para>Cluster resources cannot be removed if their ID is referenced by any
     constraint. If you cannot delete a resource, check where the resource ID is
     referenced and remove the resource from the constraint first.</para>
   </note>
   <procedure id="pro.ha.config.gui.rm">
    <title>Removing a Cluster Resource</title>
    <step>
     <para>Start the &hbgui; and log in to the cluster as described in <xref
       linkend="sec.ha.configuration.gui.intro.connect"/>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Click <guimenu>Management</guimenu> in the left pane.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Select the respective resource in the right pane.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Clean up the resource on all nodes as described in <xref
       linkend="pro.ha.config.gui.clean"/>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para><guimenu>Stop</guimenu> the resource. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Remove all constraints that relate to the resource, otherwise
      removing the resource will not be possible.</para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.ha.configuration.migrate">
   <title>Migrating Cluster Resources</title>
   <para> As mentioned in <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.failover"/>, the
    cluster will fail over (migrate) resources automatically in case of software
    or hardware failures&mdash;according to certain parameters you can
    define (for example, migration threshold or resource stickiness). Apart from
    that, you can also manually migrate a resource to another node in the
    cluster resources manually. </para>

   <procedure id="pro.ha.config.gui.migrate">
    <title>Manually Migrating a Resource</title>
    <step>
     <para> Start the &hbgui; and log in to the cluster as described in
       <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.gui.intro.connect"/>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Click <guimenu>Management</guimenu> in the left pane.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Right-click the respective resource in the right pane and select
       <guimenu>Migrate Resource</guimenu>. </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="crmgui-main-migrate.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="crmgui-main-migrate.png" width="70%" format="png"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In the new window, select the node to which to move the resource to
      in <guimenu>To Node</guimenu>. This creates a location constraint with an
       <literal>INFINITY</literal> score for the destination node. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> If you want to migrate the resource only temporarily, activate
       <guimenu>Duration</guimenu> and enter the time frame for which the
      resource should migrate to the new node. After the expiration of the
      duration, the resource <emphasis>can</emphasis> move back to its original
      location or it may stay where it is (depending on resource stickiness).
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In cases where the resource cannot be migrated (if the resource's
      stickiness and constraint scores total more than
       <literal>INFINITY</literal> on the current node), activate the
       <guimenu>Force</guimenu> option. This forces the resource to move by
      creating a rule for the current location and a score of
       <literal>-INFINITY</literal>. </para>
     <note>
      <para> This prevents the resource from running on this node until the
       constraint is removed with <guimenu>Clear Migrate Constraints</guimenu>
       or the duration expires. </para>
     </note>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to confirm the migration. </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>To allow a resource to move back again, proceed as follows:</para>
   <procedure id="pro.ha.config.gui.migrate.back">
    <title>Clearing a Migration Constraint</title>
    <step>
     <para> Start the &hbgui; and log in to the cluster as described in
       <xref linkend="sec.ha.configuration.gui.intro.connect"/>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Click <guimenu>Management</guimenu> in the left pane.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Right-click the respective resource in the right pane and select
       <guimenu>Clear Migrate Constraints</guimenu>. </para>
     <para>This uses the
      <command>crm_resource&nbsp;<option>-U</option></command> command. The
      resource <emphasis>can</emphasis> move back to its original location or it
      may stay where it is (depending on resource stickiness). </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>For more information, see <xref linkend="man.crmresource"/> or
     <citetitle>Pacemaker 1.0&mdash;Configuration Explained</citetitle>,
    available from <ulink url="http://clusterlabs.org/wiki/Documentation"/>.
    Refer to section <citetitle>Resource Migration</citetitle>. </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.ha.configuration.mgmt.mode">
   <title>Changing Management Mode of Resources</title>
   <para>When a resource is being managed by the cluster, it must not be touched
    otherwise (outside of the cluster). For maintenance of individual resources,
    you can set the respective resources to an <literal>unmanaged mode</literal>
    that allows you to modify the resource outside of the cluster.</para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>Start the &hbgui; and log in to the cluster as described in <xref
       linkend="sec.ha.configuration.gui.intro.connect"/>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Click <guimenu>Management</guimenu> in the left pane.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Right-click the respective resource in the right pane and from the
      context menu, select <guimenu>Unmanage Resource</guimenu>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>After you have finished the maintenance task for that resource,
      right-click the respective resource again in the right pane and select
       <guimenu>Manage Resource</guimenu>. </para>
     <para>From this point on, the resource will be managed by the &hasi;
      software again.</para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 </chapter>
