<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
 %entities;
]>
<!--taroth -2010-02-01: todo - https://fate.novell.com/307371
                                                     https://fate.novell.com/303384 -->
<chapter id="cha.ha.configuration.basics">
 <title>Configuration and Administration Basics</title>
 <para>
<!--taroth 2010-01-27: todo - consolidate the basics into one
  chapter as propsed by lmb and then have (sub-)chapters explaining how 
  to apply them via the GUI/CLI -->
 </para>
 <!--taroth 201002-10: also mention setting of global quorum and fencing options
  (crm tool/GUI): rgoldwyn: That is a part of cluster CIB configuration
  using the hb_gui-->
 <abstract>
  <para>
   The main purpose of an HA cluster is to manage user services. Typical
   examples of user services are an Apache web server or a database. From
   the user's point of view, the services do something specific when ordered
   to do so. To the cluster, however, they are just resources which may be
   started or stopped&mdash;the nature of the service is irrelevant to the
   cluster.
  </para>
  
  <para>
   As a cluster administrator, you need to create cluster resources for
   every resource or application you run on servers in your cluster. Cluster
   resources can include Web sites, e-mail servers, databases, file systems,
   virtual machines, and any other server-based applications or services you
   want to make available to users at all times.
  </para>
  
  <para>In this chapter, we will introduce some basic concepts you need to
   know when configuring resources and administering your cluster. The
   following chapters show you how to execute the main configuration and
   administration tasks with each of the management tools the &hasi;
   provides.</para>
 </abstract>
 
 <remark>taroth 2010-02-19: todo - for each section/topic add xrefs to the
 following chapters (GUI, HAWK, CLI)</remark>
 
 <sect1>
  <title>Cluster Resources</title>
  
  <para>
   You can create the following types of resources:
  </para>
  
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Primitive</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A primitive resource, the most basic type of a resource.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Group</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Groups contain a set of resources that need to be located together,
      start sequentially and stop in the reverse order. For more
      information, refer to
      <xref
       linkend="sec.ha.configuration.group"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Clone</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Clones are resources that can be active on multiple hosts. Any
      resource can be cloned, provided the respective resource agent
      supports it. For more information, refer to
      <xref
       linkend="sec.ha.configuration.clone"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Master</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Masters are a special type of a clone resources, masters can have
      multiple modes. Masters must contain exactly one group or one regular
      resource.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1>
  <title>Constraints</title>
  <para></para>
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1>
  <title>Failover and Failback Nodes</title>
  <para></para>
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1>
  <title>Clone Resources</title>
  <para></para>
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1>
  <title>Management: Starting, Removing, Cleaning Up, and Migrating
   Resources</title>
  <para></para>
 </sect1>
 
 
</chapter>
