<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
 %entities;
]>

<!--taroth 2010-02-10: todo: https://fate.novell.com/307380
  Testcase
setup 
1. start cmirrord 
2. vgconvert -cy $VGNAME 
3. lvcreate -m 1 ++name $LVNAME ++size $LVSIZE $VGNAME 
   A mirrored $LVNAME should be created successfully with userspace log. 
   recover: Following scenarios should be tested under stressed IO load . 
   device failure during writing
   device failure during syncing
   system crash during writing
   system crash during syncing

-->
<chapter id="cha.ha.clvm">
 <title>Cluster LVM</title>
 <abstract>
  <para>
  When managing shared storage on a cluster, every node must be informed
  about changes that are done to the storage subsystem. The Linux Volume
  Manager 2 (LVM2), which is widely used to manage local storage, has been
  extended to support transparent management of volume groups across the
  whole cluster. Clustered volume groups can be managed using the same
  commands as local storage.
 </para>
 </abstract>
 
 <sect1 id="sec.ha.clvm.overview">
  <title>Conceptual Overview</title>
  <para>
   Internally, cLVM uses the Distributed Lock Manager (DLM) component of the
   cluster stack to coordinate access to the LVM2 metadata. As DLM in turn
   integrates with the other components of the stack such as fencing, the
   integrity of the shared storage is protected at all times.
  </para>
  <para>
   cLVM does not coordinate access to the shared data itself; to do so, you
   must configure OCFS2 or other cluster-aware applications on top of the
   cLVM-managed storage.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1 id="sec.ha.clvm.config">
  <title>Configuration of cLVM</title>

  <para>Before you proceed with the cluster LVM, make sure you have
  fullfilled the following prerequisites:</para>
  
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>Make sure, a shared storage device is available, such as
     provided by a Fibre Channel, FCoE, SCSI or iSCSI SAN or DRBD
     &mdash;. </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>In case of DRBD, make both nodes primary.</para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  
  
  <para>
   To setup a cluster-aware volume group, several tasks must be completed
   successfully:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <!-- http://doccomments.provo.novell.com/admin/viewcomment/11504
 openAIS -> Corosync
    -->
    <para>If you find the following message in
     <filename>/var/log/message</filename>, configure &corosync; without
     multiple (redundant) rings:</para>
    <screen>kernel: dlm: TCP protocol can't handle multi-homed hosts,<!--
    --> try SCTP</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Check the locking type of LVM2 to be cluster-aware. 
    </para>
    <para>
     The file <filename>/etc/lvm/lvm.conf</filename> must contain the
     following line:
    </para>
<screen>locking_type = 3</screen>
    <para>Write the configuration to disk. Copy this configuration to all nodes.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Include the clvmd resource as a clone in the pacemaker configuration,
     and make it depend on the DLM clone resource. A typical snippet from
     the crm configuration shell would look like this:
    </para>
<screen>
primitive dlm ocf:pacemaker:controld
primitive clvm ocf:lvm2:clvmd \
        params daemon_timeout="30"
clone dlm-clone dlm \
        meta target-role="Started" interleave="true" ordered="true"
clone clvm-clone clvm \
        meta target-role="Started" interleave="true" ordered="true"
colocation colo-clvm inf: clvm-clone dlm-clone
order order-clvm inf: dlm-clone clvm-clone
...    
    </screen>
    <para>
     Before proceeding, confirm that these resources have started
     successfully in your cluster. You may use crm_mon or the GUI to check
     the running services.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Prepare the physical volume for LVM with the command
     <command>pvcreate</command>, for example on the device 
     <filename>/dev/sdb</filename>:
    </para>
<screen>pvcreate /dev/sdb</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Create a cluster aware volume group:
    </para>
<screen>vgcreate --clustered y myclusterfs /dev/sdb</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Create logical volumes as needed. You may probably change the size
     (4G) of the logical volume. For example:
    </para>
<screen>lvcreate --name testlv -L 4G myclusterfs</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To ensure that the volume group is activated cluster-wide, configure a
     LVM resource as follows:
    </para>
<screen>
primitive vg1 ocf:heartbeat:LVM \
        params volgrpname="myclusterfs"
clone vg1-clone vg1 \
        meta interleave="true" ordered="true"
colocation colo-vg1 inf: vg1-clone clvm-clone
order order-vg1 inf: clvm-clone vg1-clone
    </screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If you want the volume group to only be activated exclusively on one
     node, use the following example; in this case, cLVM will protect all
     logical volumes within the VG from being activated on multiple nodes,
     as an additional measure of protection for non-clustered applications:
    </para>
<screen>
primitive vg1 ocf:heartbeat:LVM \
        params volgrpname="myclusterfs" exclusive="yes"
colocation colo-vg1 inf: vg1 clvm-clone
order order-vg1 inf: clvm-clone vg1
    </screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     The logical volumes within the VG are now available as file system
     mounts or raw usage. Ensure that services using them must have proper
     dependencies to collocate them with and order them after the VG has
     been activated.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   After finishing these configuration steps, the LVM2 configuration can be
   done just like on any standalone workstation.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.ha.clvm.drbd">
  <title>Configuring Eligible LVM2 Devices Explicitly</title>

  <para>
   When several devices seemingly share the same physical volume signature
   (as can be the case for multipath devices or drbd), it is recommended to
   explicitly configure the devices which LVM2 scans for PVs.
  </para>

  <para>
   For example, if the command <command>vgcreate</command> uses the physical
   device instead of using the mirrored block device, DRBD will be confused
   which may result in a split brain condition for DRBD.
  </para>

  <para>
   To deactivate a single device for LVM2, do the following:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Edit the file <filename>/etc/lvm/lvm.conf</filename> and search for the
     line starting with <literal>filter</literal>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     The patterns there are handled as regular expressions. A leading
     <quote>a</quote> means to accept a device pattern to the scan, a
     leading <quote>r</quote> rejects the devices that follow the device
     pattern.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To remove a device named <filename>/dev/sdb1</filename>, add the
     following expression to the filter rule:
    </para>
<screen>
"r|^/dev/sdb1$|"
    </screen>
    <para>
     The complete filter line will look like the following:
    </para>
<screen>
filter = [ "r|^/dev/sdb1$|", "r|/dev/.*/by-path/.*|", "r|/dev/.*/by-id/.*|", "a/.*/" ]
    </screen>
    <para>
     A filter line, that accepts DRBD and MPIO devices but rejects all other
     devices would look like this:
    </para>
<screen>filter = [ "a|/dev/drbd.*|", "a|/dev/.*/by-id/dm-uuid-mpath-.*|",
"r/.*/" ]</screen>
   </step>
<!--   
   <step>
    <para>
     Explicitly accept all the eligible devices, and reject all others.
     For example, a filter line which accepts all MPIO and drbd devices would
     look like this:
    </para>
    <screen>filter = [ "a|/dev/drbd.*|", "a|/dev/.*/by-id/dm-uuid-mpath-.*|", "r/.*/"]</screen>
   </step> -->
   <step>
    <para>
     Write the configuration file and copy it to all cluster nodes.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.ha.clvm.more">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   Much information is available from the pacemaker mailing list, available
   at <ulink url="http://www.clusterlabs.org/wiki/Help:Contents"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   The official cLVM FAQ can be found at
   <ulink url="http://sources.redhat.com/cluster/wiki/FAQ/CLVM"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
