<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
  %entities;
]>

<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?><chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="sec-ha-config-basics-resources" xml:lang="en" version="5.1">
 <title>Configuring cluster resources</title>
 <info xmlns:d="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <abstract>
   <para>
    As a cluster administrator, you need to create cluster resources for
    every resource or application you run on servers in your cluster. Cluster
    resources can include Web sites, e-mail servers, databases, file systems,
    virtual machines and any other server-based applications or services you
    want to make available to users at all times.
   </para>
  </abstract>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker/>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 <revhistory xml:id="rh-sec-ha-config-basics-resources">
   <revision>
     <date>2025-11-19</date>
     <revdescription>
       <para/>
     </revdescription>
   </revision>
 </revhistory>
</info>

  <sect1 xml:id="sec-ha-config-basics-resources-types">
   <title>Types of resources</title>
   <para>
    The following types of resources can be created:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Primitives</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       A primitive resource, the most basic type of resource.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Groups</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Groups contain a set of resources that need to be located together,
       started sequentially and stopped in the reverse order.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Clones</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Clones are resources that can be active on multiple hosts. Any
       resource can be cloned, provided the respective resource agent
       supports it.
      </para>
      <para>
       Promotable clones (also known as multi-state resources) are a
       special type of clone resource that can be promoted.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="sec-ha-config-basics-raclasses">
   <title>Supported resource agent classes</title>
   <para>
    For each cluster resource you add, you need to define the standard that
    the resource agent conforms to. Resource agents abstract the services
    they provide and present an accurate status to the cluster, which allows
    the cluster to be non-committal about the resources it manages. The
    cluster relies on the resource agent to react appropriately when given a
    start, stop or monitor command.
   </para>
   <para>
    Typically, resource agents come in the form of shell scripts. &productname;
    supports the following classes of resource agents:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry xml:id="vle-ha-resources-ocf-ra">
     <term>Open Cluster Framework (OCF) resource agents</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       OCF RA agents are best suited for use with &ha;, especially when
       you need promotable clone resources or special monitoring abilities. The
       agents are generally located in
       <filename>/usr/lib/ocf/resource.d/<replaceable>provider</replaceable>/</filename>.
       Their functionality is similar to that of LSB scripts. However, the
       configuration is always done with environmental variables that allow
       them to accept and process parameters easily.
       OCF specifications have strict definitions of which exit codes must
       be returned by actions. See <xref linkend="sec-ha-errorcodes"/>. The
       cluster follows these specifications exactly.
      </para>
      <para>
       All OCF Resource Agents are required to have at least the actions
       <literal>start</literal>, <literal>stop</literal>,
       <literal>status</literal>, <literal>monitor</literal> and
       <literal>meta-data</literal>. The <literal>meta-data</literal> action
       retrieves information about how to configure the agent. For example,
       to know more about the <literal>IPaddr</literal> agent by
       the provider <literal>heartbeat</literal>, use the following command:
      </para>
<screen>OCF_ROOT=/usr/lib/ocf /usr/lib/ocf/resource.d/heartbeat/IPaddr meta-data</screen>
      <para>
       The output is information in XML format, including several sections
       (general description, available parameters, available actions for the
       agent).
      </para>
      <para>
       Alternatively, use the &crmsh; to view information on OCF resource
       agents. For details, see <xref linkend="sec-ha-manual-config-ocf"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Linux Standards Base (LSB) scripts</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       LSB resource agents are generally provided by the operating
       system/distribution and are found in
       <filename>/etc/init.d</filename>. To be used with the cluster, they
       must conform to the LSB init script specification. For example, they
       must have several actions implemented, which are, at minimum,
       <literal>start</literal>, <literal>stop</literal>,
       <literal>restart</literal>, <literal>reload</literal>,
       <literal>force-reload</literal> and <literal>status</literal>. For
       more information, see
       <link xlink:href="https://refspecs.linuxbase.org/LSB_4.1.0/LSB-Core-generic/LSB-Core-generic/iniscrptact.html"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
       The configuration of those services is not standardized. If you
       intend to use an LSB script with &ha;, make sure that you
       understand how the relevant script is configured. You can often find
       information about this in the documentation of the relevant package
       in
       <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/<replaceable>PACKAGENAME</replaceable></filename>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>systemd</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       &pace; can manage systemd services if they
       are present. Instead of init scripts, systemd has unit files.
       Generally, the services (or unit files) are provided by the operating
       system. In case you want to convert existing init scripts, find more
       information at
       <link xlink:href="https://0pointer.de/blog/projects/systemd-for-admins-3.html"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Service</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       There are currently many types of system
       services that exist in parallel: <literal>LSB</literal> (belonging to
       System V init), <literal>systemd</literal> and (in some
       distributions) <literal>upstart</literal>. Therefore, &pace;
       supports a special alias that figures out which one
       applies to a given cluster node. This is particularly useful when the
       cluster contains a mix of systemd, upstart and LSB services.
       &pace; tries to find the named service in the following order:
       as an LSB (SYS-V) init script, a systemd unit file or an Upstart
       job.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Nagios</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Monitoring plug-ins (formerly called Nagios plug-ins) allow to
       monitor services on remote hosts. &pace; can do remote monitoring
       with the monitoring plug-ins if they are present. For detailed
       information, see
       <xref linkend="sec-ha-config-basics-remote-nagios"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>&stonith; (fencing) resource agents</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This class is used exclusively for fencing related resources. For
       more information, see <xref linkend="cha-ha-fencing"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    The agents supplied with &productname; are written to OCF
    specifications.
   </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="sec-ha-config-basics-timeouts">
   <title>Timeout values</title>
   <para>
    Timeouts values for resources can be influenced by the following
    parameters:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <varname>op_defaults</varname> (global timeout for operations),
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      a specific timeout value defined in a resource template,
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      a specific timeout value defined for a resource.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <note>
    <title>Priority of values</title>
    <para>
     If a <emphasis>specific</emphasis> value is defined for a resource, it
     takes precedence over the global default. A specific value for a
     resource also takes precedence over a value that is defined in a
     resource template.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    Getting timeout values right is very important. Setting them too low
    results in a lot of (unnecessary) fencing operations for the
    following reasons:
   </para>
   <orderedlist spacing="normal">
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If a resource runs into a timeout, it fails and the cluster tries
      to stop it.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If stopping the resource also fails (for example, because the timeout
      for stopping is set too low), the cluster fences the node. It
      considers the node where this happens to be out of control.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
   <para>
    You can adjust the global default for operations and set any specific
    timeout values with both &crmsh; and &hawk2;. The best practice for
    determining and setting timeout values is as follows:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <title>Determining timeout values</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      Check how long it takes your resources to start and stop (under load).
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      If needed, add the <varname>op_defaults</varname> parameter and set
      the (default) timeout value accordingly:
     </para>
     <substeps performance="required">
      <step>
       <para>
        For example, set <literal>op_defaults</literal> to
        <literal>60</literal> seconds:
       </para>
 <screen>&prompt.crm.conf;<command>op_defaults timeout=60</command></screen>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        For resources that need longer periods of time, define individual
        timeout values.
       </para>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      When configuring operations for a resource, add separate
      <literal>start</literal> and <literal>stop</literal> operations. When
      configuring operations with &hawk2;, it provides useful timeout
      proposals for those operations.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="sec-ha-config-basics-resources-management">
   <title>Creating primitive resources</title>
   <para>
    Before you can use a resource in the cluster, it must be set up. For
    example, to use an Apache server as a cluster resource, set
    up the Apache server first and complete the Apache configuration before
    starting the respective resource in your cluster.
   </para>
   <para>
    If a resource has specific environment requirements, make sure they are
    present and identical on all cluster nodes. This kind of configuration
    is not managed by &productname;. You must do this yourself.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can create primitive resources using either &hawk2; or &crmsh;.
   </para>
   <note>
    <title>Do not touch services managed by the cluster</title>
    <para>
     When managing a resource with &productname;, the same resource must not
     be started or stopped otherwise (outside of the cluster, for example
     manually or on boot or reboot). The &ha; software is responsible
     for all service start or stop actions.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you need to execute testing or maintenance tasks after the services
     are already running under cluster control, make sure to put the
     resources, nodes, or the whole cluster into maintenance mode before you
     touch any of them manually. For details, see
     <xref linkend="sec-ha-maint-overview"/>.
    </para>
   </note>
   <important>
    <title>Resource IDs and node names</title>
    <para>Cluster resources and cluster nodes should be named differently.
     Otherwise, &hawk2; fails.</para>
   </important>

   <sect2 xml:id="sec-conf-hawk2-rsc-primitive">
    <title>Creating primitive resources with &hawk2;</title>
    <para>
     To create the most basic type of resource, proceed as follows:
    </para>
    <procedure xml:id="pro-conf-hawk2-primitive-add">
     <title>Adding a primitive resource with &hawk2;</title>
     <step>
      <para>
       Log in to &hawk2;:
      </para>
  <screen>https://<replaceable>HAWKSERVER</replaceable>:7630/</screen>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       From the left navigation bar, select <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Configuration</guimenu> <guimenu>Add
       Resource</guimenu> <guimenu>Primitive</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Enter a unique <guimenu>Resource ID</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       If a resource template exists on which you want to base the resource
       configuration, select the respective <guimenu>Template</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step xml:id="step-ha-config-hawk2-primitive-start">
      <para>
       Select the resource agent <guimenu>Class</guimenu> you want to use:
       <literal>lsb</literal>, <literal>ocf</literal>,
       <literal>service</literal>, <literal>stonith</literal> or
       <literal>systemd</literal>. For more information, see
       <xref linkend="sec-ha-config-basics-raclasses"/>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       If you selected <literal>ocf</literal> as class, specify the
       <guimenu>Provider</guimenu> of your OCF resource agent. The OCF
       specification allows multiple vendors to supply the same resource agent.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       From the <guimenu>Type</guimenu> list, select the resource agent you want
       to use (for example, <guimenu>IPaddr</guimenu> or
       <guimenu>Filesystem</guimenu>). A short description for this resource
       agent is displayed.
      </para>
      <note>
       <para>
        The selection you get in the <guimenu>Type</guimenu> list depends on the
        <guimenu>Class</guimenu> (and for OCF resources also on the
        <guimenu>Provider</guimenu>) you have chosen.
       </para>
      </note>
      <figure>
       <title>&hawk2;&mdash;primitive resource</title>
       <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
         <imagedata fileref="hawk2-primitive-basic.png" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
         <imagedata fileref="hawk2-primitive-basic.png" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject role="description">
          <phrase>
            In the Create Primitive screen, you can edit the Resource ID, Class, Provider,
            and Type fields. You can also edit the parameters, operations, meta attributes
            and utilization settings.
          </phrase>
        </textobject>
       </mediaobject>
      </figure>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       After you have specified the resource basics, &hawk2; shows
       the following categories. Either keep these categories as suggested by &hawk2;,
       or edit them as required.
      </para>
      <variablelist>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>Parameters (instance attributes)</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Determines which instance of a service the resource controls.
          When creating a resource, &hawk2; automatically shows any required
          parameters. Edit them to get a valid resource configuration.
         </para>
         <para>
          For more information, refer to <xref linkend="sec-ha-config-basics-inst-attr"/>.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>Operations</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Needed for resource monitoring. When creating a resource, &hawk2; displays
          the most important resource operations (<literal>monitor</literal>,
          <literal>start</literal> and <literal>stop</literal>).
         </para>
         <para>
          For more information, refer to <xref linkend="sec-ha-config-basics-operations"/>.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>Meta attributes</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Tells the CRM how to treat a specific resource. When creating a resource,
          &hawk2; automatically lists the important meta
          attributes for that resource (for example, the
          <literal>target-role</literal> attribute that defines the initial state of
          a resource. By default, it is set to <literal>Stopped</literal>, so the
          resource does not start immediately).
         </para>
         <para>
          For more information, refer to <xref linkend="sec-ha-config-basics-meta-attr"/>.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>Utilization</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Tells the CRM what capacity a certain resource requires from a node.
         </para>
         <para>
          For more information, refer to <xref linkend="sec-config-hawk2-utilization"/>.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click <guimenu>Create</guimenu> to finish the configuration. A message at the
       top of the screen shows if the action has been successful.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect2>

   <sect2 xml:id="sec-ha-manual-config-create">
    <title>Creating primitive resources with &crmsh;</title>
    <procedure xml:id="pro-ha-manual-config-create">
     <title>Adding a primitive resource with &crmsh;</title>
     <step>
      <para>
       Log in as &rootuser; and start the <command>crm</command> tool:
      </para>
  <screen>&prompt.root;<command>crm configure</command></screen>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Configure a primitive IP address:
      </para>
  <screen>&prompt.crm.conf;<command>primitive myIP IPaddr \
      params ip=127.0.0.99 op monitor interval=60s</command></screen>
      <para>
       The previous command configures a <quote>primitive</quote> with the
       name <literal>myIP</literal>. You need to choose a class (here
       <literal>ocf</literal>), provider (<literal>heartbeat</literal>), and
       type (<literal>IPaddr</literal>). Furthermore, this primitive expects
       other parameters like the IP address. Change the address to your
       setup.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Display and review the changes you have made:
      </para>
  <screen>&prompt.crm.conf;<command>show</command></screen>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Commit your changes to take effect:
      </para>
  <screen>&prompt.crm.conf;<command>commit</command></screen>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="sec-ha-config-basics-resources-advanced-groups">
   <title>Creating resource groups</title>
   <para>
    Some cluster resources depend on other components or resources. They
    require that each component or resource starts in a specific order and
    runs together on the same server as the resources it depends on. To
    simplify this configuration, you can use cluster resource groups.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can create resource groups using either &hawk2; or &crmsh;.
   </para>
   <example xml:id="ex-ha-config-resource-group">
    <title>Resource group for a web server</title>
    <para>
     An example of a resource group would be a Web server that requires an
     IP address and a file system. In this case, each component is a
     separate resource that is combined into a cluster resource group. The
     resource group would run on one or more servers. In case of a software
     or hardware malfunction, the group would fail over to another server
     in the cluster, similar to an individual cluster resource.
    </para>
   </example>
   <figure pgwide="0">
    <title>Group resource</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="webserver_groupresource_a.svg" width="70%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="webserver_groupresource_a.svg" width="63%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject role="description">
       <phrase>
         This diagram shows a box at the top, labeled <quote>Web server group resource</quote>.
         The box contains three Apps: a green App, an orange App, and a blue App. Below this,
         there are three boxes with corresponding colors: the green box is labeled with the number
         1 and <quote>IP address</quote>, the orange box is labeled with the number 2 and
         <quote>File system</quote>, and the blue box is labeled with the number 3 and
         <quote>Web server software</quote>. On the left, <quote>Load order</quote> has three
         arrows pointing to the number on each box. On the right, <quote>Individual resource</quote>
         has three arrows pointing to each box.
       </phrase>
     </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    Groups have the following properties:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Starting and stopping</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Resources are started in the order they appear in and stopped in
       reverse order.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Dependency</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If a resource in the group cannot run anywhere, then none of the
       resources located after that resource in the group is allowed to
       run.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Contents</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Groups may only contain a collection of primitive cluster resources.
       Groups must contain at least one resource, otherwise the
       configuration is not valid. To refer to the child of a group
       resource, use the child's ID instead of the group's ID.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Constraints</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Although it is possible to reference the group's children in
       constraints, it is usually preferable to use the group's name
       instead.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Stickiness</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Stickiness is additive in groups. Every <emphasis>active</emphasis>
       member of the group contributes its stickiness value to the
       group's total. So if the default
       <literal>resource-stickiness</literal> is <literal>100</literal> and
       a group has seven members (ﬁve of which are active), the group as
       a whole will prefer its current location with a score of
       <literal>500</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Resource monitoring</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To enable resource monitoring for a group, you must configure
       monitoring separately for each resource in the group that you want
       monitored.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>

   <sect2 xml:id="sec-conf-hawk2-rsc-group">
    <title>Creating resource groups with &hawk2;</title>
    <note>
     <title>Empty groups</title>
     <para>
      Groups must contain at least one resource, otherwise the configuration is
      not valid. While creating a group, &hawk2; allows you to create more
      primitives and add them to the group.
     </para>
    </note>
    <procedure xml:id="pro-conf-hawk2-group">
     <title>Adding a resource group with &hawk2;</title>
     <step>
      <para>
       Log in to &hawk2;:
      </para>
  <screen>https://<replaceable>HAWKSERVER</replaceable>:7630/</screen>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       From the left navigation bar, select <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Configuration</guimenu> <guimenu>Add Resource</guimenu>
       <guimenu>Group</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Enter a unique <guimenu>Group ID</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To define the group members, select one or multiple entries in the list of
       <guimenu>Children</guimenu>. Re-sort group members by dragging and
       dropping them into the order you want by using the <quote>handle</quote>
       icon on the right.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       If needed, modify or add <guimenu>Meta Attributes</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click <guimenu>Create</guimenu> to finish the configuration. A message at
       the top of the screen shows if the action has been successful.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
    <figure>
     <title>&hawk2;&mdash;resource group</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="hawk2-rsc-group.png" width="100%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="hawk2-rsc-group.png" width="100%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject role="description">
        <phrase>
          The Create Group screen includes a field to add a Group ID and a list of
          Children (resources). Activate the check boxes to add the selected resources
          to the group. You can also edit the group's Meta Attributes.
        </phrase>
      </textobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </sect2>

   <sect2 xml:id="sec-ha-manual-config-group">
    <title>Creating a resource group with &crmsh;</title>
    <para>
     The following example creates two primitives (an IP address and an
     e-mail resource).
    </para>
    <procedure>
     <title>Adding a resource group with &crmsh;</title>
     <step>
      <para>
       Run the <command>crm</command> command as system administrator. The
       prompt changes to <literal>&crm.live;</literal>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Configure the primitives:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.crm;<command>configure</command>
&prompt.crm.conf;<command>primitive Public-IP ocf:heartbeat:IPaddr2 \
    params ip=1.2.3.4 \
    op monitor interval=10s</command>
&prompt.crm.conf;<command>primitive Email systemd:postfix \
    op monitor interval=10s</command></screen>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Group the primitives with their relevant identifiers in the correct
       order:
      </para>
  <screen>&prompt.crm.conf;<command>group g-mailsvc Public-IP Email</command></screen>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect2>
 </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="sec-ha-config-basics-resources-advanced-clones">
   <title>Creating clone resources</title>
   <para>
    You may want certain resources to run simultaneously on multiple nodes
    in your cluster. To do this, you must configure a resource as a clone.
    Examples of resources that might be configured as clones include
    cluster file systems like OCFS2. You can clone any
    resource provided. This is supported by the resource's Resource
    Agent. Clone resources may even be configured differently depending on
    which nodes they are hosted.
   </para>
   <para>
    There are three types of resource clones:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Anonymous clones</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       These are the simplest type of clones. They behave identically
       anywhere they are running. Because of this, there can only be one
       instance of an anonymous clone active per machine.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Globally unique clones</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       These resources are distinct entities. An instance of the clone
       running on one node is not equivalent to another instance on another
       node; nor would any two instances on the same node be equivalent.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Promotable clones (multi-state resources)</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Active instances of these resources are divided into two states:
       promoted and unpromoted. These are also sometimes called primary and
       secondary. Promotable clones can be either
       anonymous or globally unique. For more information, see
       <xref linkend="sec-ha-config-basics-resources-promotable-clones"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    Clones must contain exactly one group or one regular resource.
   </para>
   <para>
    When configuring resource monitoring or constraints, clones have
    different requirements than simple resources. For details, see
    &paceex;, available from <link xlink:href="https://www.clusterlabs.org/pacemaker/doc/"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can create clone resources using either &hawk2; or &crmsh;.
   </para>

   <sect2 xml:id="sec-conf-hawk2-rsc-clone">
    <title>Creating clone resources with &hawk2;</title>
    <note>
     <title>Child resources for clones</title>
     <para>
      Clones can either contain a primitive or a group as child resources. In
      &hawk2;, child resources cannot be created or modified while creating a
      clone. Before adding a clone, create child resources and configure them as desired.
     </para>
    </note>
    <procedure xml:id="pro-conf-hawk2-clone">
     <title>Adding a clone resource with &hawk2;</title>
     <step>
      <para>
       Log in to &hawk2;:
      </para>
  <screen>https://<replaceable>HAWKSERVER</replaceable>:7630/</screen>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       From the left navigation bar, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Configuration</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Add Resource</guimenu> <guimenu>Clone</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Enter a unique <guimenu>Clone ID</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       From the <guimenu>Child Resource</guimenu> list, select the primitive or
       group to use as a subresource for the clone.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       If needed, modify or add <guimenu>Meta Attributes</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click <guimenu>Create</guimenu> to finish the configuration. A message at
       the top of the screen shows if the action has been successful.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
    <figure>
     <title>&hawk2;&mdash;clone resource</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="hawk2-clone.png" width="100%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="hawk2-clone.png" width="100%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject role="description">
        <phrase>
          The Create Clone screen includes fields to add a Clone ID and the ID of the
          Child Resource. You can also edit the clone's Meta Attributes.
        </phrase>
      </textobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </sect2>

   <sect2 xml:id="sec-ha-manual-config-clone">
    <title>Creating clone resources with &crmsh;</title>
     <para>
      To create an anonymous clone resource, first create a primitive
      resource and then refer to it with the <command>clone</command> command.
     </para>
     <procedure>
      <title>Adding a clone resource with &crmsh;</title>
      <step>
       <para>
        Log in as &rootuser; and start the <command>crm</command>
        interactive shell:
       </para>
  <screen>&prompt.root;<command>crm configure</command></screen>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Configure the primitive, for example:
       </para>
  <screen>&prompt.crm.conf;<command>primitive Apache apache \
  op monitor timeout=20s interval=10s</command></screen>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Clone the primitive:
       </para>
  <screen>&prompt.crm.conf;<command>clone cl-apache Apache</command></screen>
      </step>
     </procedure>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="sec-ha-config-basics-resources-promotable-clones">
   <title>Creating promotable clones (multi-state resources)</title>
   <para>
    Promotable clones (formerly known as multi-state resources) are a
    specialization of clones. They allow the instances to be in one of two
    operating modes: promoted or unpromoted (also known as primary or
    secondary). Promotable clones must contain
    exactly one group or one regular resource.
   </para>
   <para>
    &pace; determines which instance of the clone to promote using one of the following
    methods (or a combination of both):
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
       <para>
         If a resource agent supports promotable clones, it might automatically set
         <emphasis>promotion scores</emphasis> based on its own preference for which
         instance to promote.
       </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
       <para>
         You can manually set promotion rules or preferences by creating
         <emphasis>location</emphasis> or <emphasis>colocation</emphasis> constraints.
       </para>
     </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    For more information, see <link xlink:href="https://clusterlabs.org/projects/pacemaker/doc/3.0/Pacemaker_Explained/html/collective.html#determining-which-instance-is-promoted"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    When configuring resource monitoring or constraints, promotable
    clones have different requirements than simple resources. For more information, see
    <link xlink:href="https://clusterlabs.org/projects/pacemaker/doc/3.0/Pacemaker_Explained/html/collective.html#clone-constraints"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can create promotable clones using either &hawk2; or &crmsh;.
   </para>

   <sect2 xml:id="sec-conf-hawk2-rsc-ms">
    <title>Creating promotable clones with &hawk2;</title>
<!-- tahliar 2025-11-18: Hawk2 UI still says multi-state instead of promotable as of 15 SP7. -->
    <note>
     <title>Child resources for promotable clones</title>
     <para>
      Promotable clones can either contain a primitive or a group as child
      resources. In &hawk2;, child resources cannot be created or modified while
      creating a promotable clone. Before adding a promotable clone,
      create child resources and configure them as desired. See
      <xref linkend="sec-conf-hawk2-rsc-primitive"/> or
      <xref linkend="sec-conf-hawk2-rsc-group"/>.
     </para>
    </note>
    <procedure xml:id="pro-conf-hawk2-ms">
     <title>Adding a promotable clone with &hawk2;</title>
     <step>
      <para>
       Log in to &hawk2;:
      </para>
  <screen>https://<replaceable>HAWKSERVER</replaceable>:7630/</screen>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       From the left navigation bar, select <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Configuration</guimenu>  <guimenu>Add Resource</guimenu>
       <guimenu>Multi-state</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Enter a unique <guimenu>Multi-state ID</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       From the <guimenu>Child Resource</guimenu> list, select the primitive or
       group to use as a subresource for the multi-state resource.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       If needed, modify or add <guimenu>Meta Attributes</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click <guimenu>Create</guimenu> to finish the configuration. A message at
       the top of the screen shows if the action has been successful.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect2>

   <sect2 xml:id="sec-ha-manual-config-clone-stateful">
    <title>Creating promotable clones with &crmsh;</title>
    <para>
     To create a promotable clone resource, first create a primitive resource
     and then the promotable clone resource. The promotable clone resource must
     support at least promote and demote operations.
    </para>
    <procedure>
     <title>Adding a promotable clone with &crmsh;</title>
     <step>
      <para>
       Log in as &rootuser; and start the <command>crm</command>
       interactive shell:
      </para>
 <screen>&prompt.root;<command>crm configure</command></screen>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Configure the primitive. Change the intervals if needed:
      </para>
 <screen>&prompt.crm.conf;<command>primitive my-rsc ocf:myCorp:myAppl \
    op monitor interval=60 \
    op monitor interval=61 role=Promoted</command></screen>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Create the promotable clone resource:
      </para>
 <screen>&prompt.crm.conf;<command>clone clone-rsc my-rsc meta promotable=true</command></screen>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect2>
  </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-ha-config-basics-resources-templates">
   <title>Creating resource templates</title>
   <para>
    If you want to create lots of resources with similar configurations,
    defining a resource template is the easiest way. After being
    defined, it can be referenced in primitives, or in certain types
    of constraints as described in <xref linkend="sec-ha-config-basics-constraints-templates"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    If a template is referenced in a primitive, the primitive inherits
    all operations, instance attributes (parameters), meta attributes and
    utilization attributes defined in the template. Additionally, you can
    define specific operations or attributes for your primitive. If any of
    these are defined in both the template and the primitive, the values
    defined in the primitive take precedence over the ones defined in
    the template.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can create resource templates using either &hawk2; or &crmsh;.
   </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-conf-hawk2-rsc-template">
   <title>Creating resource templates with &hawk2;</title>
    <para>
     Resource templates are configured like primitive resources.
    </para>
   <procedure xml:id="pro-conf-hawk2-template-add">
    <title>Adding a resource template</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      Log in to &hawk2;:
     </para>
 <screen>https://<replaceable>HAWKSERVER</replaceable>:7630/</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      From the left navigation bar, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Configuration</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Add Resource</guimenu> <guimenu>Template</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Enter a unique <guimenu>Resource ID</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Follow the instructions in <xref linkend="pro-conf-hawk2-primitive-add"/>,
      starting from
      <xref linkend="step-ha-config-hawk2-primitive-start" xrefstyle="select:label"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-ha-manual-config-rsc-template">
   <title>Creating resource templates with &crmsh;</title>
   <para>
    Use the <command>rsc_template</command> command to get familiar with the syntax:
   </para>
 <screen>&prompt.root;<command>crm configure rsc_template</command>
 usage: rsc_template &lt;name&gt; [&lt;class&gt;:[&lt;provider&gt;:]]&lt;type&gt;
        [params &lt;param&gt;=&lt;value&gt; [&lt;param&gt;=&lt;value&gt;...]]
        [meta &lt;attribute&gt;=&lt;value&gt; [&lt;attribute&gt;=&lt;value&gt;...]]
        [utilization &lt;attribute&gt;=&lt;value&gt; [&lt;attribute&gt;=&lt;value&gt;...]]
        [operations id_spec
            [op op_type [&lt;attribute&gt;=&lt;value&gt;...] ...]]</screen>
   <para>
    For example, the following command creates a new resource template with
    the name <literal>BigVM</literal> derived from the
    <literal>ocf:heartbeat:Xen</literal> resource and some default values
    and operations:
   </para>
 <screen>&prompt.crm.conf;<command>rsc_template BigVM ocf:heartbeat:Xen \
   params allow_mem_management="true" \
   op monitor timeout=60s interval=15s \
   op stop timeout=10m \
   op start timeout=10m</command></screen>
   <para>
    Once you define the new resource template, you can use it in primitives
    or reference it in order, colocation or rsc_ticket constraints. To
    reference the resource template, use the <literal>@</literal> sign:
   </para>
 <screen>&prompt.crm.conf;<command>primitive MyVM1 @BigVM \
   params xmfile="/etc/xen/shared-vm/MyVM1" name="MyVM1"</command></screen>
   <para>
    The new primitive MyVM1 is going to inherit everything from the BigVM
    resource templates. For example, the equivalent of the above two would
    be:
   </para>
 <screen>&prompt.crm.conf;<command>primitive MyVM1 Xen \
   params xmfile="/etc/xen/shared-vm/MyVM1" name="MyVM1" \
   params allow_mem_management="true" \
   op monitor timeout=60s interval=15s \
   op stop timeout=10m \
   op start timeout=10m</command></screen>
   <para>
    If you want to overwrite some options or operations, add them to your
    (primitive) definition. For example, the following new primitive MyVM2
    doubles the timeout for monitor operations but leaves others untouched:
   </para>
 <screen>&prompt.crm.conf;<command>primitive MyVM2 @BigVM \
   params xmfile="/etc/xen/shared-vm/MyVM2" name="MyVM2" \
   op monitor timeout=120s interval=30s</command></screen>
   <para>
    A resource template may be referenced in constraints to stand for all
    primitives which are derived from that template. This helps to produce a
    more concise and clear cluster configuration. Resource template
    references are allowed in all constraints except location constraints.
    Colocation constraints may not contain more than one template reference.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

<sect1 xml:id="sec-ha-conf-stonith-rsc">
 <title>Creating &stonith; resources</title>
   &important-stonith;
  <para>
   By default, the global cluster option <literal>stonith-enabled</literal> is
   set to <literal>true</literal>. If no &stonith; resources have been defined,
   the cluster refuses to start any resources. Configure one or more
   &stonith; resources to complete the &stonith; setup. While &stonith; resources
   are configured similarly to other resources, their behavior is different in
   some respects. For details refer to <xref linkend="sec-ha-fencing-config"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   You can create &stonith; resources using either &hawk2; or &crmsh;.
  </para>
 <sect2 xml:id="sec-conf-hawk2-rsc-stonith">
  <title>Creating &stonith; resources with &hawk2;</title>
  <para>
   To add a &stonith; resource for SBD, for libvirt (&kvm;/&xen;), or for vCenter/ESX Server,
   the easiest way is to use the &hawk2; wizard.
  </para>
  <procedure xml:id="pro-conf-hawk2-stonith">
   <title>Adding a &stonith; resource with &hawk2;</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Log in to &hawk2;:
    </para>
<screen>https://<replaceable>HAWKSERVER</replaceable>:7630/</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     From the left navigation bar, select <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Configuration</guimenu> <guimenu>Add
     Resource</guimenu> <guimenu>Primitive</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter a unique <guimenu>Resource ID</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     From the <guimenu>Class</guimenu> list, select the resource agent class
     <guimenu>stonith</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     From the <guimenu>Type</guimenu> list, select the &stonith; plug-in to
     control your &stonith; device. A short description for this plug-in is
     displayed.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     &hawk2; automatically shows the required <guimenu>Parameters</guimenu> for
     the resource. Enter values for each parameter.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     &hawk2; displays the most important resource <guimenu>Operations</guimenu>
     and proposes default values. If you do not modify any settings,
     &hawk2; adds the proposed operations and their default values when you
     confirm.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If there is no reason to change them, keep the default <guimenu>Meta
     Attributes</guimenu> settings.
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>&hawk2;&mdash;&stonith; resource</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="hawk2-primitive-stonith.png" width="100%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="hawk2-primitive-stonith.png" width="100%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject role="description">
        <phrase>
          This example of the Create Primitive screen shows a primitive called
          <literal>stonith-1</literal>, with the class <literal>stonith</literal>
          and the type <literal>apcmaster</literal>. The parameters include an
          <literal>ipaddr</literal>, <literal>login</literal> and <literal>password</literal>.
          It has <literal>start</literal>, <literal>stop</literal> and <literal>monitor</literal>
          operations. It also has the meta attribute <literal>target-role</literal> set to
          <literal>Stopped</literal>.
        </phrase>
      </textobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Confirm your changes to create the &stonith; resource.
    </para>
    <para>
     A message at the top of the screen shows if the action has been
     successful.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>
   To complete your fencing configuration, add constraints. For more details,
   refer to <xref linkend="cha-ha-fencing"/>.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-ha-manual-create-stonith">
  <title>Creating &stonith; resources with &crmsh;</title>
  <procedure>
   <title>Adding a &stonith; resource with &crmsh;</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Log in as &rootuser; and start the <command>crm</command>
     interactive shell:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>crm</command></screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Get a list of all &stonith; types with the following command:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.crm;<command>ra list stonith</command>
apcmaster                  apcmastersnmp              apcsmart
baytech                    bladehpi                   cyclades
drac3                      external/drac5             external/dracmc-telnet
external/hetzner           external/hmchttp           external/ibmrsa
external/ibmrsa-telnet     external/ipmi              external/ippower9258
external/kdumpcheck        external/libvirt           external/nut
external/rackpdu           external/riloe             external/sbd
external/vcenter           external/vmware            external/xen0
external/xen0-ha           fence_legacy               ibmhmc
ipmilan                    meatware                   nw_rpc100s
rcd_serial                 rps10                      suicide
wti_mpc                    wti_nps</screen>
   </step>
   <step xml:id="st-ha-manual-create-stonith-type">
    <para>
     Choose a &stonith; type from the above list and view the list of
     possible options. Use the following command:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.crm;<command>ra info stonith:external/ipmi</command>
IPMI STONITH external device (stonith:external/ipmi)

ipmitool based power management. Apparently, the power off
method of ipmitool is intercepted by ACPI which then makes
a regular shutdown. In case of a split brain on a two-node,
it may happen that no node survives. For two-node clusters,
use only the reset method.

Parameters (* denotes required, [] the default):

hostname (string): Hostname
   The name of the host to be managed by this STONITH device.
...</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Create the &stonith; resource with the <literal>stonith</literal>
     class, the type you have chosen in
     <xref linkend="st-ha-manual-create-stonith-type" xrefstyle="select:label nopage"/>,
     and the respective parameters if needed, for example:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.crm;<command>configure</command>
&prompt.crm.conf;<command>primitive my-stonith stonith:external/ipmi \
   params hostname="&node1;" \
   ipaddr="&subnetI;.221" \
   userid="admin" passwd="secret" \
   op monitor interval=60m timeout=120s</command></screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect2>
</sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-ha-config-basics-monitoring">
  <title>Configuring resource monitoring</title>
  <para>
   If you want to ensure that a resource is running, you must configure
   resource monitoring for it. You can configure resource monitoring using
   either &hawk2; or &crmsh;.
  </para>
  <para>
   If the resource monitor detects a failure, the following takes place:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Log file messages are generated, according to the configuration
     specified in the <literal>logging</literal> section of
     <filename>/etc/corosync/corosync.conf</filename>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The failure is reflected in the cluster management tools (&hawk2;,
     <command>crm status</command>), and in the CIB status section.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The cluster initiates noticeable recovery actions, which may include
     stopping the resource to repair the failed state and restarting the
     resource locally or on another node. The resource also may not be
     restarted, depending on the configuration and state of the cluster.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   If you do not configure resource monitoring, resource failures after a
   successful start are not communicated, and the cluster will always
   show the resource as healthy.
  </para>
   <para>
    Usually, resources are only
    monitored by the cluster while they are running. However, to detect
    concurrency violations, also configure monitoring for resources which are
    stopped. For resource monitoring, specify a timeout and/or start delay
    value, and an interval. The interval tells the CRM how often it should check
    the resource status. You can also set particular parameters such as
    <literal>timeout</literal> for <literal>start</literal> or
    <literal>stop</literal> operations.
   </para>
   <para>
    For more information about monitor operation parameters, see
    <xref linkend="sec-ha-config-basics-operations"/>.
   </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-conf-hawk2-rsc-monitor">
   <title>Configuring resource monitoring with &hawk2;</title>
   <procedure xml:id="pro-hawk2-operations">
    <title>Adding and modifying an operation</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      Log in to &hawk2;:
     </para>
 <screen>https://<replaceable>HAWKSERVER</replaceable>:7630/</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Add a resource as described in
      <xref linkend="pro-conf-hawk2-primitive-add"/> or select an existing
      primitive to edit.
     </para>
     <para>
      &hawk2; automatically shows the most important
      <guimenu>Operations</guimenu> (<literal>start</literal>,
      <literal>stop</literal>, <literal>monitor</literal>) and proposes default
      values.
     </para>
     <para>
      To see the attributes belonging to each proposed value, hover the mouse
      pointer over the respective value.
     </para>
     <figure>
      <title>Operation values</title>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="hawk2-monitor-op.png" width="70%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="hawk2-monitor-op.png" width="60%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <textobject role="description">
         <phrase>
           In the <literal>Operations</literal> list, beside the <literal>monitor</literal>
           operation, hovering the mouse pointer over the number <literal>20</literal> shows
           that this is the value for the <literal>timeout</literal> attribute.
         </phrase>
       </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </figure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To change the suggested <literal>timeout</literal> values for the
      <literal>start</literal> or <literal>stop</literal> operation:
     </para>
     <substeps>
      <step>
       <para>
        Click the pen icon next to the operation.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        In the dialog that opens, enter a different value for the
        <literal>timeout</literal> parameter, for example <literal>10</literal>,
        and confirm your change.
       </para>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To change the suggested <guimenu>interval</guimenu> value for the
      <literal>monitor</literal> operation:
     </para>
     <substeps>
      <step>
       <para>
        Click the pen icon next to the operation.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        In the dialog that opens, enter a different value for the monitoring
        <literal>interval</literal>.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        To configure resource monitoring in the case that the resource is
        stopped:
       </para>
       <substeps>
        <step>
         <para>
          Select the <literal>role</literal> entry from the empty drop-down box
          below.
         </para>
        </step>
        <step>
         <para>
          From the <literal>role</literal> drop-down box, select
          <literal>Stopped</literal>.
         </para>
        </step>
        <step>
         <para>
          Click <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> to confirm your changes and to close
          the dialog for the operation.
         </para>
        </step>
       </substeps>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Confirm your changes in the resource configuration screen. A message at
      the top of the screen shows if the action has been successful.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    To view resource failures, switch to the <guimenu>Status</guimenu> screen in
    &hawk2; and select the resource you are interested in. In the
    <guimenu>Operations</guimenu> column click the arrow down icon and select
    <guimenu>Recent Events</guimenu>. The dialog that opens lists recent actions
    performed for the resource. Failures are displayed in red. To view the
    resource details, click the magnifier icon in the
    <guimenu>Operations</guimenu> column.
   </para>
   <figure>
    <title>&hawk2;&mdash;resource details</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="hawk2-rsc-details.png" width="70%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="hawk2-rsc-details.png" width="60%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject role="description">
       <phrase>
         This example shows the details of an <literal>nfsserver</literal> resource. It has the
         Meta Attribute <literal>target-role</literal> set to <literal>Stopped</literal>, along
         with <literal>start</literal>, <literal>stop</literal>, and <literal>monitor</literal>
         Operations.
       </phrase>
     </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-ha-manual-config-monitor">
   <title>Configuring resource monitoring with &crmsh;</title>
   <para>
    To monitor a resource, there are two possibilities: either define a
    monitor operation with the <command>op</command> keyword or use the
    <command>monitor</command> command. The following example configures an
    Apache resource and monitors it every 60 seconds with the
    <literal>op</literal> keyword:
   </para>
 <screen>&prompt.crm.conf;<command>primitive apache apache \
  params ... \
  <emphasis>op monitor interval=60s timeout=30s</emphasis></command></screen>
   <para>
    The same can be done with the following commands:
   </para>
 <screen>&prompt.crm.conf;<command>primitive apache apache \
   params ...</command>
 &prompt.crm.conf;<command>monitor apache 60s:30s</command></screen>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Monitoring stopped resources</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Usually, resources are only monitored by the cluster while they
       are running. However, to detect concurrency violations, also configure
       monitoring for resources which are stopped. For example:
      </para>
 <screen>&prompt.crm.conf;<command>primitive dummy1 Dummy \
     op monitor interval="300s" role="Stopped" timeout="10s" \
     op monitor interval="30s" timeout="10s"</command></screen>
      <para>
       This configuration triggers a monitoring operation every
       <literal>300</literal> seconds for the resource
       <literal>dummy1</literal> when it is in
       <literal>role="Stopped"</literal>. When running, it is monitored
       every <literal>30</literal> seconds.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Probing</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The CRM executes an initial monitoring for each resource on every
       node, the so-called <literal>probe</literal>. A probe is also executed
       after the cleanup of a resource. If multiple monitoring operations are
       defined for a resource, the CRM selects the one with the smallest
       interval and uses its timeout value as default timeout for
       probing. If no monitor operation is configured, the cluster-wide
       default applies. The default is <literal>20</literal> seconds (if not
       specified otherwise by configuring the <varname>op_defaults</varname>
       parameter). If you do not want to rely on the automatic calculation or
       the <systemitem>op_defaults</systemitem> value, define a specific
       monitoring operation for the <emphasis>probing</emphasis> of this
       resource. Do so by adding a monitoring operation with the
       <literal>interval</literal> set to <literal>0</literal>, for example:
      </para>
 <screen>&prompt.crm.conf;<command>primitive rsc1 ocf:pacemaker:Dummy \
     op monitor interval="0" timeout="60"</command></screen>
      <para>
       The probe of <systemitem>rsc1</systemitem> times out in
       <literal>60s</literal>, independent of the global timeout defined in
       <varname>op_defaults</varname>, or any other operation timeouts
       configured. If you did not set <literal>interval="0"</literal> for
       specifying the probing of the respective resource, the CRM
       automatically checks for any other monitoring operations defined for
       that resource and calculates the timeout value for probing as
       described above.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-ha-manual-config-load">
  <title>Loading resources from a file</title>
  <para>
   Parts or all of the configuration can be loaded from a local file or a
   network URL. Three different methods can be defined:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><option>replace</option></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This option replaces the current configuration with the new source
      configuration.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><option>update</option></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This option tries to import the source configuration. It adds new items
      or updates existing items to the current configuration.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><option>push</option></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This option imports the content from the source into the current
      configuration (same as <option>update</option>). However, it removes
      objects that are not available in the new configuration.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>
   To load the new configuration from the file <filename>mycluster-config.txt</filename>
   use the following syntax:
  </para>
  <screen>&prompt.root;<command>crm configure load push mycluster-config.txt</command></screen>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-ha-config-basics-meta-attr">
  <title>Resource options (meta attributes)</title>
  <para>
   For each resource you add, you can define options. Options are used by
   the cluster to decide how your resource should behave; they tell
   the CRM how to treat a specific resource. Resource options can be set
   with the <command>crm_resource --meta</command> command or with &hawk2;.
  </para>
  <para>
   The following list shows some common options:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>priority</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If not all resources can be active, the cluster stops lower-priority
      resources to keep higher-priority resources active.
     </para>
     <para>
      The default value is <literal>0</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>target-role</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      In what state should the cluster attempt to keep this resource?
      Allowed values: <literal>Stopped</literal>, <literal>Started</literal>,
      <literal>Unpromoted</literal>, <literal>Promoted</literal>.
     </para>
     <para>
      The default value is <literal>Started</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>is-managed</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Is the cluster allowed to start and stop the resource? Allowed
      values: <literal>true</literal>, <literal>false</literal>. If the
      value is set to <literal>false</literal>, the status of the
      resource is still monitored and any failures are reported. This is
      different from setting a resource to
      <literal>maintenance="true"</literal>.
     </para>
     <para>
      The default value is <literal>true</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>maintenance</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Can the resources be touched manually? Allowed values:
      <literal>true</literal>, <literal>false</literal>. If set to
      <literal>true</literal>, all resources become unmanaged: the
      cluster stops monitoring them and does not know their
      status. You can stop or restart cluster resources without
      the cluster attempting to restart them.
     </para>
     <para>
      The default value is <literal>false</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>resource-stickiness</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      How much does the resource prefer to stay where it is?
     </para>
     <para>
      The default value is <literal>1</literal> for individual clone instances,
      and <literal>0</literal> for all other resources.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>migration-threshold</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      How many failures should occur for this resource on a node before
      making the node ineligible to host this resource?
     </para>
     <para>
      The default value is <literal>INFINITY</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>multiple-active</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      What should the cluster do if it ever finds the resource active on
      more than one node? Allowed values: <literal>block</literal> (mark
      the resource as unmanaged), <literal>stop_only</literal>,
      <literal>stop_start</literal>.
     </para>
     <para>
      The default value is <literal>stop_start</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>failure-timeout</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      How many seconds to wait before acting as if the failure did not
      occur (and potentially allowing the resource back to the node on
      which it failed)?
     </para>
     <para>
      The default value is <literal>0</literal> (disabled).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>allow-migrate</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Whether to allow live migration for resources that support
      <literal>migrate_to</literal> and <literal>migrate_from</literal>
      actions. If the value is set to <literal>true</literal>, the resource can
      be migrated without loss of state. If the value is set to <literal>false</literal>,
      the resource will be shut down on the first node and restarted on the second node.
     </para>
     <para>
      The default value is <literal>true</literal> for
      <literal>ocf:pacemaker:remote</literal> resources, and
      <literal>false</literal> for all other resources.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>allow-unhealthy-nodes</literal></term>
     <listitem>
       <para>
        Allows the resource to run on a node even if the node's health score would otherwise
        prevent it.
       </para>
       <para>
         The default value is <literal>false</literal>.
       </para>
     </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>remote-node</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The name of the remote node this resource defines. This both
      enables the resource as a remote node and defines the unique name
      used to identify the remote node. If no other parameters are set,
      this value is also assumed as the host name to connect to at the
      <varname>remote-port</varname> port.
     </para>
     <para>
      This option is disabled by default.
     </para>
     <warning>
      <title>Use unique IDs</title>
      <para>
       This value must not overlap with any existing resource or node IDs.
      </para>
     </warning>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>remote-port</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Custom port for the guest connection to pacemaker_remote.
     </para>
     <para>
      The default value is <literal>3121</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>remote-addr</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The IP address or host name to connect to if the remote node's
      name is not the host name of the guest.
     </para>
     <para>
      The default value is the value set by <literal>remote-node</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>remote-connect-timeout</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      How long before a pending guest connection times out?
     </para>
     <para>
      The default value is <literal>60s</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-ha-config-basics-inst-attr">
  <title>Instance attributes (parameters)</title>

  <para>
   The scripts of all resource classes can be given parameters which
   determine how they behave and which instance of a service they control.
   If your resource agent supports parameters, you can add them with the
   <command>crm_resource</command> command or with &hawk2;. In the
   <command>crm</command> command line utility and in &hawk2;, instance
   attributes are called <literal>params</literal> or
   <literal>Parameter</literal>, respectively. The list of instance
   attributes supported by an OCF script can be found by executing the
   following command as &rootuser;:
  </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>crm ra info <replaceable>[class:[provider:]]resource_agent</replaceable></command></screen>
  <para>
   or (without the optional parts):
  </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>crm ra info <replaceable>resource_agent</replaceable></command></screen>
  <para>
   The output lists all the supported attributes, their purpose and default
   values.
  </para>
  <note>
   <title>Instance attributes for groups, clones or promotable clones</title>
   <para>
    Note that groups, clones and promotable clone resources do not have instance
    attributes. However, any instance attributes set are inherited by
    the group's, clone's or promotable clone's children.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-ha-config-basics-operations">
  <title>Resource operations</title>
  <para>
   By default, the cluster does not ensure that your resources are still
   healthy. To instruct the cluster to do this, you need to add a monitor
   operation to the resource's definition. Monitor operations can be
   added for all classes or resource agents.
  </para>
  <para>
   Monitor operations can have the following properties:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>id</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Your name for the action. Must be unique. (The ID is not shown.)
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>name</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The action to perform. Common values: <literal>monitor</literal>,
        <literal>start</literal>, <literal>stop</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>interval</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      How frequently to perform the operation, in seconds.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>timeout</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      How long to wait before declaring the action has failed.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>requires</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      What conditions need to be satisfied before this action occurs.
      Allowed values: <literal>nothing</literal>,
      <literal>quorum</literal>, <literal>fencing</literal>. The default
      depends on whether fencing is enabled and if the resource's class
      is <literal>stonith</literal>. For &stonith; resources, the
      default is <literal>nothing</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>on-fail</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The action to take if this action ever fails. Allowed values:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <literal>ignore</literal>: Pretend the resource did not fail.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <literal>block</literal>: Do not perform any further operations
        on the resource.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <literal>stop</literal>: Stop the resource and do not start it
        elsewhere.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <literal>restart</literal>: Stop the resource and start it again
        (possibly on a different node).
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <literal>fence</literal>: Bring down the node on which the
        resource failed (&stonith;).
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <literal>standby</literal>: Move <emphasis>all</emphasis>
        resources away from the node on which the resource failed.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>enabled</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If <literal>false</literal>, the operation is treated as if it does
      not exist. Allowed values: <literal>true</literal>,
      <literal>false</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>role</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Run the operation only if the resource has this role.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>record-pending</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Can be set either globally or for individual resources. Makes the
        CIB reflect the state of <quote>in-flight</quote> operations on
        resources.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>description</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Description of the operation.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>

</chapter>
