<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<preface id="pre.ha">
 <title>About This Guide</title>
 <para> &productnamereg; is an integrated suite of open source clustering
  technologies that enables you to implement highly available physical and
  virtual Linux clusters. For your convenience, the
  &hasi; includes both graphical tools (like several &yast; modules or the Web
  interface &hawk;), and command line interfaces (CLI), such as the &crmshell;, for
  example. </para>
 <para> This guide is intended for administrators who need to set up, configure,
  and maintain &ha; (HA) clusters. For performing key tasks, both approaches
  (graphical Web interface and CLI) are covered in detail. Thus, administrators
  can choose the appropriate tool that matches their needs. </para>
 <para>
  This guide is divided into the following parts:
 </para>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part.install" xrefstyle="select:title,nopage"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Before starting to install and configure your cluster, make yourself
     familiar with cluster fundamentals and architecture, get an overview of
     the key features and benefits. Learn which hardware and software
     requirements must be met and what preparations to take before executing
     the next steps. Perform the installation and basic setup of your HA
     cluster using &yast;.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part.config" xrefstyle="select:title,nopage"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para> Add, configure and manage cluster resources with either the Web
     interface (&hawk;), or the command line interface (&crmsh;). To
     avoid unauthorized access to the cluster configuration, define roles and
     assign them to certain users for fine-grained control. Learn how to use 
     load balancing and fencing. If you consider writing your own resource agents or modifying existing
     ones, get some background information on how to create different types of
     resource agents. </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part.storage" xrefstyle="select:title,nopage"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para> &productname; ships with the cluster-aware file systems OCFS2 and
     GFS2, and the clustered Logical Volume Manager (cLVM). For replication of
     your data, use DRBD*. It lets you mirror the data of a &ha; service from the
     active node of a cluster to its standby node. Furthermore, a clustered
     Samba server also provides a &ha; solution for heterogeneous
     environments. </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part.appendix" xrefstyle="select:title,nopage"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>Contains an overview of common problems and their solution. Presents the
     naming conventions used in this documentation with regard to clusters,
     resources and constraints. Shows the published documentation updates 
     including a detailed list of the content changes for each update. 
     Contains a glossary with HA-specific terminology.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
 <para>
  Many chapters in this manual contain links to additional documentation
  resources. These include additional documentation that is available on the
  system as well as documentation available on the Internet.
 </para>
 <para>
  For an overview of the documentation available for your product and the
  latest documentation updates, refer to
  <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/doc/"/>.
 </para>
<!--<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  href="common_intro_available_doc_i.xml"/>-->
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="common_intro_feedback_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="common_intro_typografie_i.xml"/>
</preface>
