<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<preface id="pre.ha">
 <title>About This Guide</title>
 <para> &productnamereg; is an integrated suite of open source clustering
  technologies that enables you to implement highly available physical and
  virtual Linux clusters. For quick and efficient configuration and
  administration, the &hasi; includes several &yast; modules as graphical user
  interface (GUI), the Web interface &hawk;, and &crmsh; as
  command line interface (CLI). </para>
 <para>
  This guide is intended for administrators who need to set up, configure,
  and maintain &ha; (HA) clusters. Both approaches (graphical Web interface and CLI) are covered
  in detail to help the administrators choose the appropriate tool that
  matches their needs for performing the key tasks.
 </para>
 <para>
  This guide is divided into the following parts:
 </para>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part.install" xrefstyle="select:title,nopage"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Before starting to install and configure your cluster, make yourself
     familiar with cluster fundamentals and architecture, get an overview of
     the key features and benefits. Learn which hardware and software
     requirements must be met and what preparations to take before executing
     the next steps. Perform the installation and basic setup of your HA
     cluster using &yast;.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part.config" xrefstyle="select:title,nopage"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Add, configure and manage cluster resources, using either the Web 
     interface (&haweb;), or the command line interface 
     (<command>crm</command> shell). To avoid unauthorized
     access to the cluster configuration, define roles and assign them to
     certain users for fine-grained control. Learn how to make use of load
     balancing and fencing or how to set up a multi-site cluster. In case
     you consider writing your own resource agents or modifying existing
     ones, get some background information on how to create different types
     of resource agents.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part.storage" xrefstyle="select:title,nopage"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para> &productname; ships with the cluster-aware file systems OCFS2 and
     GFS2 and the clustered Logical Volume Manager (cLVM). For replication of
     your data, use DRBD* to mirror the data of a &ha; service from the
     active node of a cluster to its standby node. Furthermore, a clustered
     Samba server also provides a &ha; solution for heterogeneous
     environments. </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part.appendix" xrefstyle="select:title,nopage"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Lists the new features and behavior changes of the &hasi; since the
     last release. Learn how to migrate your cluster to the most recent
     release version and find an example of setting up a simple testing
     resource.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
 <para>
  Many chapters in this manual contain links to additional documentation
  resources. These include additional documentation that is available on the
  system as well as documentation available on the Internet.
 </para>
 <para>
  For an overview of the documentation available for your product and the
  latest documentation updates, refer to
  <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/doc/sle_ha"/>.
 </para>
<!--<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  href="common_intro_available_doc_i.xml"/>-->
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="common_intro_feedback_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="common_intro_typografie_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="common_intro_making_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" os="osuse" href="common_intro_source_code_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" os="osuse" href="common_intro_acknowl_i.xml"/>
</preface>
