<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<preface  version="5.0" xml:id="pre-ha"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>About This Guide</title>
 <info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:maintainer/>
        <dm:status>editing</dm:status>
        <dm:deadline/>
        <dm:priority/>
        <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
        <dm:languages/>
        <dm:release/>
        <dm:repository/>
      </dm:docmanager>
  <abstract><para>&abstract-admin;</para> </abstract>
 </info>
 <para>
  This guide is divided into the following parts:
 </para>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part-install" xrefstyle="select:title,nopage"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Before starting to install and configure your cluster, make yourself
     familiar with cluster fundamentals and architecture, get an overview of
     the key features and benefits. Learn which hardware and software
     requirements must be met and what preparations to take before executing
     the next steps. Perform the installation and basic setup of your HA
     cluster using &yast;. Learn how to upgrade your cluster to the most recent
     release version or how to update individual packages.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part-config" xrefstyle="select:title,nopage"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Add, configure and manage cluster resources with either the Web
     interface (&hawk2;), or the command line interface (&crmsh;). To
     avoid unauthorized access to the cluster configuration, define roles
     and assign them to certain users for fine-grained control. Learn how to
     use load balancing and fencing. If you consider writing your own
     resource agents or modifying existing ones, get some background
     information on how to create different types of resource agents.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part-storage" xrefstyle="select:title,nopage"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     &productname; ships with the cluster-aware file systems OCFS2 and
     GFS2, and the clustered Logical Volume Manager (cLVM). For replication
     of your data, use DRBD*. It lets you mirror the data of a &ha;
     service from the active node of a cluster to its standby node.
     Furthermore, a clustered Samba server also provides a &ha; solution
     for heterogeneous environments.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part-appendix" xrefstyle="select:title,nopage"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>Contains an overview of common problems and their solution. Presents the
     naming conventions used in this documentation with regard to clusters,
     resources and constraints. Shows the published documentation updates 
     including a detailed list of the content changes for each update. 
     Contains a glossary with HA-specific terminology.</para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
 <para>
  Many chapters in this manual contain links to additional documentation
  resources, either on the system or available on the Internet.
 </para>
 <para>
  For an overview of the documentation available for your product and the
  latest documentation updates, refer to
  <link xlink:href="http://www.suse.com/doc/"/>.
 </para>
  <xi:include href="common_intro_available_doc_i.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="common_intro_feedback_i.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="common_intro_typografie_i.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="common_intro_making_i.xml"/>
</preface>
