<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:novdoc-profile.xsl"
  type="text/xml" 
  title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN"
                      "novdocx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entities;
]>
<sect1 id="sec_ha_quick_iscsi_intro">
 <title>Introduction</title>
 <para>
   SCSI is an implementation of the SCSI protocol over IP. In iSCSI, servers
   (targets) provide storage services to clients (initiators) over IP based
   networks using SCSI semantics. On iSCSI initiator nodes, logical units
   (LUs) appear like any other SCSI block device, where they may be
   partitioned, used to hold filesystem storage, used to contain raw data,
   etc.
  </para>

  <para>
   At the time of writing, several competing iSCSI target implementations
   exist on the Linux platform. Two of them are covered in this white paper:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     iSCSI Enterprise Target (IET). This was the first production-ready
     iSCSI target implementation for Linux. It uses a split, part-kernel,
     part-userland configuration interface that requires both a specific
     kernel module, and a running management daemon (ietd). The in-kernel
     implementation has not been merged into the mainline Linux kernel tree.
     Still, IET is included and fully supported as part of SUSE Linux
     Enterprise Server (versions 10 and 11), and Debian 5.0
     (<literal>lenny</literal>). Although IET development had quieted down
     at one time, the project is currently quite active and has a small, but
     very productive core development team.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Linux SCSI Target Framework (tgt). This aims to be a generic SCSI
     target framework for Linux, of which an iSCSI target is merely an
     implementation (or lower-level driver in tgt terms). The generic
     in-kernel framework that tgt uses is part of mainline Linux since
     release 2.6.20, and has been back-ported to the Red Hat Enterprise
     Linux 5 patched 2.6.18 kernel series. As such, it is fully supported on
     RHEL 5 and CentOS 5 from update 3 onwards; in previous RHEL releases it
     had been available as a technology preview only. tgt is also available
     in RHEL 6 and SLES 11.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</sect1>