<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<!--taroth 2011-11-25: maintainer of ipvsadmin: marius tomaschewski-->
<!-- 
toms 2014-05-27:
* Restructured file to make it easier to describe both LVS and HAProxy
* Let Darix/Lars proofread that file.
-->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha-ha-lb">
<!--taroth 090519: see http://www.linuxvirtualserver.org/-->
 <title>Load balancing</title>
 <info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:maintainer/>
        <dm:status>editing</dm:status>
        <dm:deadline/>
        <dm:priority/>
        <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
        <dm:languages/>
        <dm:release/>
        <dm:repository/>
      </dm:docmanager>
 <abstract>
  <para>
  <emphasis>Load Balancing</emphasis> makes a cluster of servers appear as
  one large, fast server to outside clients. This apparent single server is
  called a <emphasis>virtual server</emphasis>. It consists of one or more
  load balancers dispatching incoming requests and several real servers
  running the actual services. With a load balancing setup of &hasi;, you
  can build highly scalable and highly available network services, such as
  Web, cache, mail, FTP, media and VoIP services.
 </para>
 </abstract>
 </info>
    <!--taroth 090519: see http://www.linuxvirtualserver.org/-->
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-ha-lb-overview">
  <title>Conceptual overview</title>
  <para>
   &hasi; supports two technologies for load balancing: &lvs; (LVS) and
   &haproxy;. The key difference is &lvs; operates at OSI layer 4
   (Transport), configuring the network layer of kernel, while &haproxy;
   operates at layer 7 (Application), running in user space. Thus &lvs;
   needs fewer resources and can handle higher loads, while &haproxy; can
   inspect the traffic, do SSL termination and make dispatching decisions
   based on the content of the traffic.
  </para>
  <para>
   On the other hand, &lvs; includes two different software:
   IPVS (IP Virtual Server) and KTCPVS (Kernel TCP Virtual Server).
   IPVS provides layer 4 load balancing whereas KTCPVS provides layer 7
   load balancing.
  </para>
  <para>
   This section gives you a conceptual overview of load balancing
   in combination with high availability, then briefly introduces you
   to &lvs; and &haproxy;. Finally, it points you to further reading.
  </para>
  <para>
   The real servers and the load balancers may be interconnected by either
   high-speed LAN or by geographically dispersed WAN. The load balancers
   dispatch requests to the different servers. They make parallel services
   of the cluster appear as one virtual service on a single IP address (the
   virtual IP address or VIP). Request dispatching can use IP load balancing
   technologies or application-level load balancing technologies.
   Scalability of the system is achieved by transparently adding or removing
   nodes in the cluster.
  </para>

  <para>
   High availability is provided by detecting node or service failures and
   reconfiguring the whole virtual server system appropriately, as usual.
  </para>

  <remark>Most of the following items are taken from FATE#316459. Not
  sure if this is really correct. Needs technical proofreading by an
  expert.</remark>

  <para>
   There are several load balancing strategies. Here are some Layer 4
   strategies, suitable for &lvs;:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Round robin</title>
     <para>
      The simplest strategy is to direct each connection to a different
      address, taking turns. For example, a DNS server can have several
      entries for a given host name. With DNS round robin, the DNS server
      will return all of them in a rotating order. Thus different clients
      will see different addresses.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Selecting the <quote>best</quote> server</title>
     <para>
      Although this has several drawbacks, balancing could be implemented
      with an <quote>the first server who responds</quote> or <quote>the
      least loaded server</quote> approach.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Balance number of connections per server</title>
     <para>
      A load balancer between users and servers can divide the number of
      users across multiple servers.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Geo location</title>
     <para>
      It is possible to direct clients to a server nearby.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   Here are some Layer 7 strategies, suitable for &haproxy;:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>URI</title>
     <para>
      Inspect the HTTP content and dispatch to a server most suitable for
      this specific URI.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>URL parameter, RDP cookie</title>
     <para>
      Inspect the HTTP content for a session parameter, possibly in post
      parameters, or the RDP (remote desktop protocol) session cookie, and
      dispatch to the server serving this session.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   Although there is some overlap, &haproxy; can be used in scenarios
   where LVS/<command>ipvsadm</command> is not adequate and vice versa:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>SSL termination</title>
     <para>
      The front-end load balancers can handle the SSL layer. Thus the cloud
      nodes do not need to have access to the SSL keys, or could take
      advantage of SSL accelerators in the load balancers.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Application level</title>
     <para>
      &haproxy; operates at the application level, allowing the load
      balancing decisions to be influenced by the content stream. This
      allows for persistence based on cookies and other such filters.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   On the other hand, LVS/<command>ipvsadm</command> cannot be fully
   replaced by &haproxy;:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     LVS supports <quote>direct routing</quote>, where the load balancer is
     only in the inbound stream, whereas the outbound traffic is routed to
     the clients directly. This allows for potentially much higher
     throughput in asymmetric environments.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     LVS supports stateful connection table replication (via
     <systemitem class="daemon">conntrackd</systemitem>). This allows for
     load balancer failover that is transparent to the client and server.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>

 <xi:include href="ha_lb_lvs.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="ha_lb_haproxy.xml"/>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-ha-lb-more">
  <title>For more information</title>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><link xlink:href="http://www.haproxy.org"/></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Project home page at <link xlink:href="http://www.linuxvirtualserver.org/"/>.
  </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>For more information about <systemitem class="daemon">ldirectord</systemitem>, refer to its
        comprehensive man page.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>LVS Knowledge Base: <link xlink:href="http://kb.linuxvirtualserver.org/wiki/Main_Page"/></para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
</chapter>