<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
 %entities;
]>
<appendix id="cha.ha.changes">
 <title>What's New?</title>
 <para>
  The software modifications from version to version are outlined in detail
  in the following sections. This summary indicates, for example, whether
  basic settings have been completely reconfigured, configuration files have
  been moved to other places, or other significant changes happened.
 </para>
 <sect1 id="sec.ha.changes.sle11">
  <title>Version 10 SP3 to Version 11</title>

  <para>
   With &sls; 11, the cluster stack has changed from &hb; to &ais;. &ais;
   implements an industry standard API, the Application Interface
   Specification (AIS), published by the Service Availability Forum. The
   cluster resource manager from &sls; 10 has been retained but has been
   significantly enhanced, ported to &ais; and is now known as Pacemaker.
  </para>

  <para>
   For more details what changed in the &ha; components from &slsreg; 10 SP3
   to &sls; 11, refer to the following sections.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.ha.changes.sle11.new">
   <title>New Features and Functions Added</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry id="vle.ha.news.fail">
     <term>Migration Threshold and Failure Timeouts</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The &hasi; now comes with the concept of a migration threshold and
       failure timeout. You can define a number of failures for resources,
       after which they will migrate to a new node. By default, the node
       will no longer be allowed to run the failed resource until the
       administrator manually resets the resource’s failcount. However it
       is also possible to expire them by setting the resource’s
       <literal>failure-timeout</literal> option.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry id="vle.ha.news.defaults">
     <term>Resource and Operation Defaults</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       You can now set global defaults for resource options and operations.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Support for Offline Configuration Changes</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Often it is desirable to preview the effects of a series of changes
       before updating the configuration atomically. You can now create a
       <quote>shadow</quote> copy of the configuration that can be edited
       with the command line interface, before committing it and thus
       changing the active cluster configuration atomically.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Reusing Rules, Options and Sets of Operations</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Rules, instance_attributes, meta_attributes and sets of operations
       can be defined once and referenced in multiple places.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Using XPath Expressions for Certain Operations in the CIB</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The CIB now accepts XPath-based <literal>create</literal>,
       <literal>modify</literal>, <literal>delete</literal> operations. For
       more information, refer to the <command>cibadmin</command> help text.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Multi-dimensional Collocation and Ordering Constraints</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       For creating a set of collocated resources, previously you could
       either deﬁne a resource group (which could not always accurately
       express the design) or you could deﬁne each relationship as an
       individual constraint&mdash;causing a constraint explosion as the
       number of resources and combinations grew. Now you can also use an
       alternate form of collocation constraints by defining
       <literal>resource_sets</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Connection to the CIB From Non-cluster Machines</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Provided Pacemaker is installed on a machine, it is possible to
       connect to the cluster even if the machine itself is not a part of
       it.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Triggering Recurring Actions at Known Times</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       By default, recurring actions are scheduled relative to when the
       resource started, but this is not always desirable. To specify a
       date/time that the operation should be relative to, set the
       operation’s interval-origin. The cluster uses this point to
       calculate the correct start-delay such that the operation will occur
       at origin + (interval * N).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.ha.changes.sle11.changed">
   <title>Changed Features and Functions</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry id="vle.ha.news.options">
     <term>Naming Conventions for Resource and Custer Options</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       All resource and cluster options now use dashes (-) instead of
       underscores (_). For example, the <literal>master_max</literal> meta
       option has been renamed to <literal>master-max</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Renaming of <literal>master_slave</literal> Resource </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The <literal>master_slave</literal> resource has been renamed to
       <literal>master</literal>. Master resources are a special type of
       clone that can operate in one of two modes.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Container Tag for Attributes</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The <literal>attributes</literal> container tag has been removed.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Operation Field for Prerequisites</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The <literal>pre-req</literal> operation field has been renamed
       <literal>requires</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Interval for Operations</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       All operations must have an interval. For start/stop actions the
       interval must be set to <literal>0</literal> (zero).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Attributes for Collocation and Ordering Constraints</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The attributes of collocation and ordering constraints were renamed
       for clarity.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Cluster Options for Migration Due to Failure</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The <literal>resource-failure-stickiness</literal> cluster option has
       been replaced by the <literal>migration-threshold</literal> cluster
       option. See also <xref linkend="vle.ha.news.fail"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Arguments for Command Line Tools</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The arguments for command-line tools have been made consistent. See
       also <xref linkend="vle.ha.news.options"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Validating and Parsing XML</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The cluster configuration is written in XML. Instead of a Document
       Type Definition (DTD), now a more powerful RELAX&nbsp;NG schema is
       used to define the pattern for the structure and content.
       <literal>libxml2</literal> is used as parser.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>id</literal> Fields</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>id</literal> fields are now XML IDs which have the following
       limitations:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         IDs cannot contain colons.
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         IDs cannot begin with a number.
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         IDs must be globally unique (not just unique for that tag).
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>References to Other Objects</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Some fields (such as those in constraints that refer to resources)
       are IDREFs. This means that they must reference existing resources or
       objects in order for the configuration to be valid. Removing an
       object which is referenced elsewhere will therefore fail.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.ha.changes.sle11.removed">
   <title>Removed Features and Functions</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Setting Resource Meta Options</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       It is no longer possible to set resource meta-options as top-level
       attributes. Use meta attributes instead. See also the
       <command>crm_resource</command> man page.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Setting Global Defaults</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Resource and operation defaults are no longer read from
       <literal>crm_conﬁg</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.ha.changes.sle11.sp1">
  <title>Version 11 to Version 11 SP1</title>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Cluster Configuration File</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The main cluster configuration file has changed from
      <filename>/etc/ais/openais.conf</filename> to
      <filename>/etc/corosync/corosync.conf</filename>. Both files are very
      similar. When upgrading from &sle; &hasi; 11 to SP1, a script takes
      care of the minor differences between those files. For more
      information about the relationship between &ais; and &corosync;, see
      <ulink url="http://www.corosync.org/doku.php?id=faq:why">.</ulink>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Rolling Upgrade</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      In order to migrate existing clusters with minimal downtime,
      &productname; allows you to perform a <quote>rolling upgrade</quote>
      from &productname; 11 to 11 SP1. The cluster is still online while you
      upgrade one node after the other.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Automatic Cluster Deployment</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      For easier cluster deployment, &ay; allows you to clone existing
      nodes. &ay; is a system for installing one or more &sle; systems
      automatically and without user intervention, using an &ay; profile
      that contains installation and configuration data. The profile tells
      &ay; what to install and how to configure the installed system to get
      a completely ready-to-use system in the end. This profile can be used
      for mass deployment in different ways.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Transfer of Configuration Files </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      &productname; ships with &csync;, a tool for replication of
      configuration files across all nodes in the cluster. It can handle any
      number of hosts and it is also possible to synchronize files among
      certain subgroups of hosts only. Use &yast; to configure the hostnames
      and the files that should be synchronized with &csync;.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Web-Interface for Cluster Management</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The &hasi; now also includes the &haweb; (&hawk;), a Web-based user interface
      for management tasks. It allows you to monitor and administer your
      Linux cluster also from non-Linux machines. It is also an ideal
      solution in case your system does not provide or allow a graphical
      user interface.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Templates for Resource Configuration </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      When using the command line interface to create and configure
      resources, you can now choose from various resource templates for
      quicker and easier configuration.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Load-based Placement of Resources</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      By defining the capacity a certain node <emphasis>provides</emphasis>,
      the capacity a certain resource <emphasis>requires</emphasis> and by
      choosing one of several placement strategies in the cluster, resources
      can be placed according to their load impact to prevent decrease of
      cluster performance.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Cluster-aware Active/Active RAID1</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      It is now possible to create disaster-resilient storage configurations
      from two independent SANs, using
      <systemitem class="daemon"
       >cmirrord</systemitem>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Read-only GFS2 Support</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      For easier migration from GFS2 to OCFS2, you can mount your GFS2 file
      systems in read-only mode to copy the data to an OCFS2 file system.
      OCFS2 is fully supported by &productname;.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>SCTP Support for OCFS2 </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If redundant rings are configured, OCFS2 and DLM can automatically use
      redundant communication paths via SCTP, independent of network device
      bonding.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Storage Protection</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      For additional layers of security in protecting your storage from data
      corruption, you can use a combination of IO fencing (with the
      <literal>external/sbd</literal> fencing device) and the
      <systemitem
       class="resource">sfex</systemitem> resource agent
      to ensure exclusive storage access.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Samba Clustering</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The &hasi; now supports CTDB, the cluster implementation of the
      trivial database. This allows you configure a clustered Samba
      server&mdash;providing an &ha; solution also for heterogeneous
      environments.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>&yast; Module for IP Load Balancing</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The new module allows configuration of kernel-based load balancing
      with a graphical user interface. It is a front-end for
      <systemitem
       class="daemon">ldirectord</systemitem>, a
      user-space daemon for managing &lvs; and monitoring the real servers.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
</appendix>
