<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha-ha-storage-dlm">
 <title>Distributed Lock Manager (DLM)</title>
 <info>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    The Distributed Lock Manager (DLM) in the kernel is the base component used
    by &ocfs;, GFS2, Cluster MD, and &clvm; (lvmlockd) to provide active-active
    storage at each respective layer.
   </para>
  </abstract>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-ha-storage-dlm-protocol">
  <title>Protocols for DLM communication</title>

  <para>
   To avoid single points of failure, redundant communication paths are important
   for &ha; clusters. This is also true for DLM communication. If network bonding
   (Link Aggregation Control Protocol, LACP) cannot be used for any reason, we
   highly recommend to define a redundant communication channel (a second ring)
   in &corosync;. For details, see <xref
   linkend="pro-ha-installation-setup-channel2"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   Depending on the configuration in &corosync.conf;, DLM then decides
   whether to use the TCP or SCTP protocol for its communication:
  </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
     If <guimenu>rrp_mode</guimenu> is set to <literal>none</literal> (which
     means redundant ring configuration is disabled), DLM automatically uses
     TCP. However, without a redundant communication channel, DLM communication
     will fail if the TCP link is down.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
     If <guimenu>rrp_mode</guimenu> is set to <literal>passive</literal> (which
     is the typical setting), and a second communication ring in &corosync.conf;
     is configured correctly, DLM automatically uses SCTP. In this case, DLM
     messaging has the redundancy capability provided by SCTP.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-ha-storage-generic-dlm-config">
  <title>Configuring DLM cluster resources</title>

  <para>
   DLM uses the cluster membership services from &pace; which run in user
   space. Therefore, DLM needs to be configured as a clone resource that is
   present on each node in the cluster.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>DLM resource for several solutions</title>
   <para>
    As &ocfs;, GFS2, Cluster MD, and &clvm; (lvmlockd) all use DLM, it is
    enough to configure one resource for DLM. As the DLM resource runs on all
    nodes in the cluster it is configured as a clone resource.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you have a setup that includes both &ocfs; and &clvm;, configuring
    <emphasis>one</emphasis> DLM resource for both &ocfs; and &clvm; is enough.
   </para>
  </note>

  <procedure xml:id="pro-dlm-resources">
   <title>Configuring a base group for DLM</title>
   <para>
    The configuration consists of a base group that includes several primitives
    and a base clone. Both base group and base clone can be used in various
    scenarios afterward (for both &ocfs; and &clvm;, for example). You only need
    to extend the base group with the respective primitives as needed. As the
    base group has internal colocation and ordering, this simplifies the
    overall setup as you do not need to specify several individual groups,
    clones and their dependencies.
   </para>
   <para>
    Follow the steps below on one node in the cluster:
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start a shell and log in as &rootuser; or equivalent.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Run <command>crm</command> <option>configure</option>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the following to create the primitive resource for DLM:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.crm.conf;<command>primitive</command> dlm ocf:pacemaker:controld \
  op monitor interval="60" timeout="60"</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Create a base group for the DLM resource and further storage-related
     resources:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.crm.conf;<command>group</command> g-storage dlm</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Clone the <literal>g-storage</literal> group so that it runs on all nodes:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.crm.conf; <command>clone</command> cl-storage g-storage \
  meta interleave=true target-role=Started</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Review your changes with <command>show</command>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If everything is correct, submit your changes with
     <command>commit</command> and leave the crm live configuration with
     <command>quit</command>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <note>
   <title>Failure when disabling &stonith;</title>
   <para>
    Clusters without &stonith; are not supported. If you set the global cluster
    option <varname>stonith-enabled</varname> to <literal>false</literal> for
    testing or troubleshooting purposes, the DLM resource and all services
    depending on it (such as &clvm;, GFS2, and OCFS2) will fail to start.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
