<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:base="common_intro_feedback_i.xml" version="5.0">
 <title>Giving Feedback</title>

 <info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:translation>no</dm:translation>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <para>
  Your feedback and contribution to this documentation is welcome!
  Several channels are available:
 </para>

 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry os="sles;sled">
   <term>Service Requests and Support</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     For services and support options available for your product, refer to
     <link xlink:href="http://www.suse.com/support/"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
     To open a service request, you need a subscription at SUSE Customer Center. Go to
     <link xlink:href="https://scc.suse.com/support/requests"/>, log in, and click
     <guimenu>Create New</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Bug Reports</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Report issues with the documentation at <link os="sles;sled" xlink:href="https://bugzilla.suse.com/"/>.
     To simplify this process, you can use the <guimenu>Report
      Documentation Bug</guimenu> links next to headlines in the HTML
     version of this document. These preselect the right product and
     category in Bugzilla and add a link to the current section.
     You can start typing your bug report right away. A Bugzilla
     account is required.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Contributions</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To contribute to this documentation, use the <guimenu>Edit Source</guimenu>
     links next to headlines in the HTML version of this document. They
     take you to the source code on GitHub, where you can open a pull request.
     A GitHub account is required.
    </para>
     <para>
     For more information about the documentation environment used for this
     documentation, see <link xlink:href="https://github.com/SUSE/doc-sleha/blob/master/README.adoc">the repository's
      README</link>.
     
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Mail</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Alternatively, you can report errors and send feedback concerning the
     documentation to <email>doc-team@suse.com</email>. Make sure to include the
     document title, the product version and the publication date of the
     documentation. Refer to the relevant section number and title (or
     include the URL) and provide a concise description of the problem.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  
 </variablelist>
</sect1>
