<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:base="common_intro_available_doc_i.xml" version="5.0">
 <title>Available Documentation</title>

 <info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
          
        </dm:bugtracker>
        <dm:translation>no</dm:translation>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <indexterm>

 <primary>help</primary>

 <secondary>SUSE manuals</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

 <primary>SUSE manuals</primary></indexterm>

 <note>
  <title>Online Documentation and Latest Updates</title>
  <para>
   Documentation for our products is available at
   <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/"/>, where you can also
   find the latest updates, and browse or download the documentation in various formats.
   The latest documentation updates can usually be found in the English language version.
  </para>
 </note>
 <para>The following documentation is available for this product:
 </para>
  <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Installation and Setup Quick Start
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      This document guides you through the setup of a very basic two-node cluster,
    using the bootstrap scripts provided by the
    <systemitem class="resource">ha-cluster-bootstrap</systemitem> package.
    This includes the configuration of a virtual IP address as a cluster
    resource and the use of SBD on shared storage as a node fencing mechanism.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Administration Guide
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      This guide is intended for administrators who need to set up, configure,
  and maintain clusters with <phrase role="roductnamereg"><phrase os="sles">SUSE® Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension</phrase></phrase>. For quick and efficient 
  configuration and administration, the product includes both a graphical user
  interface and a command line interface (CLI). For performing key tasks,
  both approaches are covered in this guide. Thus, you can choose the appropriate
  tool that matches your needs.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Highly Available NFS Storage with DRBD and Pacemaker
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      This document describes how to set up highly available NFS storage in a
    two-node cluster, using the following components:
    DRBD* (Distributed Replicated Block Device), LVM (Logical Volume Manager), 
    and Pacemaker as cluster resource manager.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Pacemaker Remote Quick Start
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      This document guides you through the setup of a High Availability cluster with a remote
   node or a guest node, managed by Pacemaker and <systemitem class="daemon">pacemaker_remote</systemitem>.
   <emphasis>Remote</emphasis> in <systemitem class="daemon">pacemaker_remote</systemitem>
   does not refer to physical distance, but to the special status of nodes that
   do not run the complete cluster stack and thus are not regular members of the
   cluster.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Geo Clustering Quick Start
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      Geo clustering protects workloads across globally distributed data
   centers. This document guides you through the basic setup of a
   Geo cluster, using the Geo bootstrap scripts provided by the
   <systemitem class="resource">ha-cluster-bootstrap</systemitem>
   package.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Geo Clustering Guide
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      This document covers the setup options and parameters for Geo clusters and
   their components, such as booth ticket manager, the specific Csync2 setup, and the
   configuration of the required cluster resources (and how to transfer them to
   other sites in case of changes). Learn how to monitor and manage Geo clusters
   from command line or with the Hawk2 Web interface.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
</sect1>
