<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<preface xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:base="ha_intro.xml" version="5.0" xml:id="pre-ha">
 <title>About This Guide</title>
 <info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:maintainer/>
        <dm:status>editing</dm:status>
        <dm:deadline/>
        <dm:priority/>
        <dm:translation>no</dm:translation>
        <dm:languages/>
        <dm:release/>
        <dm:repository/>
      </dm:docmanager>
      <abstract>
        <para> This guide is intended for administrators who need to set up, configure,
  and maintain clusters with <phrase role="roductnamereg"><phrase os="sles">SUSE® Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension</phrase></phrase>. For quick and efficient 
  configuration and administration, the product includes both a graphical user
  interface and a command line interface (CLI). For performing key tasks,
  both approaches are covered in this guide. Thus, you can choose the appropriate
  tool that matches your needs.</para>
      </abstract>
    </info>
    <para>
  This guide is divided into the following parts:
 </para>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part-install" xrefstyle="select:title,nopage"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Before starting to install and configure your cluster, make yourself
     familiar with cluster fundamentals and architecture, get an overview of
     the key features and benefits. Learn which hardware and software
     requirements must be met and what preparations to take before executing
     the next steps. Perform the installation and basic setup of your HA
     cluster using YaST. Learn how to upgrade your cluster to the most recent
     release version or how to update individual packages.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part-config" xrefstyle="select:title,nopage"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Add, configure and manage cluster resources with either the Web
     interface (Hawk2), or the command line interface (crmsh). To
     avoid unauthorized access to the cluster configuration, define roles
     and assign them to certain users for fine-grained control. Learn how to
     use load balancing and fencing. If you consider writing your own
     resource agents or modifying existing ones, get some background
     information on how to create different types of resource agents.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part-storage" xrefstyle="select:title,nopage"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <phrase role="productname"><phrase os="sles">SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension</phrase></phrase> ships with the cluster-aware file systems OCFS2 and
     GFS2, and the Cluster Logical Volume Manager (Cluster LVM). For
     replication of your data, use DRBD*. It lets you mirror the data
     of a High Availability service from the active node of a cluster to its standby
     node. Furthermore, a clustered Samba server also provides a High Availability
     solution for heterogeneous environments.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part-appendix" xrefstyle="select:title,nopage"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>Contains an overview of common problems and their solution. Presents the
     naming conventions used in this documentation with regard to clusters,
     resources and constraints.  
     Contains a glossary with HA-specific terminology.</para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
  <xi:include href="common_intro_available_doc_i.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="common_intro_feedback_i.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="common_intro_typografie_i.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="common_intro_lifecycle_support_i.xml"/>
</preface>
